<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The pearle of perfection sought after by Charles Odingsells, Doctour of Divinitie</title>
            <author>Odingsells, Charles, d. 1637.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1637</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 171 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 53 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A08457</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 18782</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S113411</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99848645</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99848645</idno>
            <idno type="VID">13754</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A08457)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 13754)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1110:11)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The pearle of perfection sought after by Charles Odingsells, Doctour of Divinitie</title>
                  <author>Odingsells, Charles, d. 1637.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 96 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by M. D[awson] for Iohn Williams, at the signe of the Crane in Pauls Church-yard,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1637.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Printer's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Perfection --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:13754:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:13754:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE PEARLE OF PERFECTION SOVGHT AFTER <hi>By</hi> CHARLES ODINGSELLS, Doctour of Divinitie.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>GEN. 17.1.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>I am the Almightie God, walke before me, and be thou perfect.</p>
            </q>
            <p>LONDON, Printed by <hi>M.D.</hi> for <hi>Iohn Williams,</hi> at the ſigne of the <hi>Crane</hi> in <hi>Pauls</hi> Church-yard. 1637.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:13754:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:13754:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>TO THE MOST REVEREND FATHER in GOD, RICHARD, Lord Arch biſhop of <hi>Yorke</hi> his Grace, Primate of ENGLAND and <hi>Metropolitane; And one of his</hi> MAIESTIES <hi>moſt Honourable Privie Councell.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Here are not a few, who with NAAMAN the <hi>Syrian</hi> take greater delight in <hi>Abana</hi> and <hi>Tharpar,</hi> rivers of <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maſcus,</hi> than in <hi>Iordane,</hi> wherein our Saviour was baptized, than in the waters of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> the holy waters of <hi>Sailo,</hi> which run gent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly; than in the living waters of the <hi>Sanctu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>arie;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ezek. 47 9.</note> which given <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> to them which
<pb facs="tcp:13754:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>mooue therein. Theſe are they who after the vulgar eſtimation, prepoſterouſly judge the fine meale of pure literature to be courſe bran, and their own courſe bran of humane knowledge and obſervation to be fine meale: who with <hi>Aeſops</hi> Cocke refuſe the pearle, and chooſe the barley corne. Such I deſire not to pleaſe, but thoſe who are <hi>meliore luto, of a better mould and temper,</hi> of ſounder reſolution and judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. The argument of perfection, wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy to be intreated of, is handled by me, not as I would, much leſſe as it requireth, but ſo as by reaſon of my bodily infirmi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties and other defects I could. I haue propounded this briefe indigeſt worke, as a ſhort modell and briefe draught to be curiouſly poliſhed and embelliſhed by ſome others, to whom God hath beene pleaſed to giue a greater meaſure of know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, with more health and ſtrength of bodie, and withall a richer Librarie, a ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciall helpe not in the laſt place requiſite. For ſurely as in other Sciences and arts, ſo alſo in our tranſcendent Science of Theologie, the Philoſophers rule is true,
<pb facs="tcp:13754:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>:<note place="margin">Ariſt. polit. li. <hi>3.</hi> ca. <hi>12.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>He that ſhall excell in his worke, muſt haue excellent tooles to worke withall.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the meane time, I am bold to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent unto your <hi>Grace</hi> this <hi>imperfect worke of perfection,</hi> in token of my dutifull and hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble reſpect to your <hi>Lordſhip,</hi> our moſt wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy <hi>Metropolitane</hi> and <hi>Dioceſan.</hi> To whom wee under your <hi>Graces</hi> juriſdiction doe by good right owe all canonicall obedience and obſervance: unto whom I in parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular doe earneſtly deſire and wiſh all ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall and corporall happineſſe here on earth; and after, everlaſting fruition of eternall glorie and felicitie in the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vens.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Graces in all humble dutie to command, <hi>CHARLES ODINGSELLS.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:13754:4" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:13754:4" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>A Table of all the principall things contained in the ſeverall Chapters of this Booke.</head>
            <list>
               <item>
                  <hi>Chapter. 1.</hi> 
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE Proeme to perfection <hi>Folio. 1</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Chapter. 2.</hi> The etymologie of perfection <hi>Folio. 3</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Chapter. 3.</hi> The divers kindes of perfection. <hi>Folio. 4</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Chapter. 4.</hi> Of Spirituall perfection. <hi>Folio. 5</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Chapter. 5.</hi> Of perfection in the ſtate of grace. <hi>Folio. 7</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Chapter. 6.</hi> Concerning knowledge. <hi>Folio. 9</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Chapter. 7.</hi> Concerning knowledge ſupernaturall. <hi>Folio. 12</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Chapter. 8.</hi> Of the knowledge of God by affection, and not bare apprehenſion onely. <hi>Folio. 15</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Chapter. 9.</hi> Of the knowledge of God in Chriſt. <hi>Folio. 16</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Chapter. 10.</hi> Concerning Chriſts Incarnation. <hi>Folio. 18</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Chapter. 11.</hi> Concerning Christs Paſſion. <hi>Folio. 20</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Chapter. 12.</hi> Concerning Christs Reſurrection. <hi>Folio. 22</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Chapter. 13.</hi> Concerning Christs Interceſſion. <hi>Folio. 24</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Chapter. 14.</hi> Of our union with Chriſt. <hi>Folio. 26</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Chapter. 15.</hi> Of the knowledge of ourſelves neceſſary to perfection. <hi>Folio. 28</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Chapter. 16.</hi> Of the further knowledge of our ſelues. <hi>Folio. 31</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Chapter. 17.</hi> Of righteouſneſſe perfecting the will <hi>Folio. 33</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Chapter. 18.</hi> Of righteouſneſſe imputed. <hi>Folio. 35</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <pb facs="tcp:13754:5" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <hi>Chapter. 19.</hi> Of imputed righteouſneſſe made ours by faith. <hi>Folio. 37</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Chapter. 20.</hi> Of the different participating of imputed righteouſneſſe by faith. <hi>Folio. 39</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Chapter. 21.</hi> Of righteouſneſſe inherent, and firſt of righteouſneſſe according to morall Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſophie. <hi>Folio. 43</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Chapter. 22.</hi> How Chriſtian inherent righteouſneſſe differeth from morall righteouſneſſe. <hi>Folio. 45</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Chapter. 23.</hi> Of the nature of inherent righteouſneſſe. <hi>Folio. 48</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Chapter. 24.</hi> Of the fruits of inherent juſtice. <hi>Folio. 49</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Chapter. 25.</hi> Of the nature and qualitie of good workes. <hi>Folio. 52</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Chapter. 26.</hi> That no man by his owne righteouſneſſe keepeth the Law, and is without ſinne. <hi>Folio. 56</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Chapter. 27.</hi> Of the growth and increaſe of inherent righteouſneſſe. <hi>Folio. 61</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Chapter. 28.</hi> Of ſpirituall ſloath, an enemy to perfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction. <hi>Folio. 64</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Chapter. 29.</hi> Of three evill qualities in ſpirituall ſloath. <hi>Folio. 67</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Chapter. 30.</hi> What perfection of inherent righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe is attainable in this life. <hi>Folio. 70</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Chapter. 31.</hi> Of perfect righteouſneſſe in this life more punctually and plainly. <hi>Folio. 73</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Chapter. 32.</hi> Concerning Perſeverance. <hi>Folio. 76</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Chapter. 33.</hi> Of perfection in Glorie. <hi>Folio. 80</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Chapter. 34.</hi> Of perfection by immortalitie in Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie. <hi>Folio. 87</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Chapter. 35.</hi> Of different perfection in Glorie. <hi>Folio. 91</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:13754:5" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>THE PEARLE OF PERFECTION.</head>
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. I.</hi> The Proeme to Perfection.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE generations of men had been multiplyed upon the face of the earth, above five thouſand yeares before the mines of gold were found out in the <hi>Weſterne Indies.</hi> And no marvaile, ſeeing the ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall gold of the Sanctuarie, the ſaving Truth of God in Chriſt, was not diſcovered unto the <hi>Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiles,</hi> to Kingdomes, and Nations, untill the world had continued in blindneſſe and ignorance well-nigh foure thouſand yeares. But as humane truth, which with <hi>Gollins</hi> is <hi>temporis filia,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Gell. noct. art. lib. <hi>12.</hi> cap. <hi>11</hi>
                  </note> the daughter of time, though ſhee be long buryed deepe below, yet remaines not alwayes in the darke night of obſcuritie, but commeth at length
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:13754:6" rendition="simple:additions"/>to light. So the divine and heavenly truth was not alwayes to bee concealed from the miſerable lapſed progenie of <hi>Adam</hi> but by the providence of God was in due time revealed; even <hi>in pleni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tudine temporis,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Gal. 4.4.</note> in the fulneſſe of time, in the ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepted time,<note place="margin">2 Cor. 6.2.</note> in the day of ſalvation. Then the Meſſias, the Life and the Truth came into the world; then the deſire of the Nations, the bright morning Starre appeared in our fleſh, full of grace and truth. And He, He ſet mens hearts on fire, inflaming them with the loue of truth: Hee excited and ſtirred up the mindes of men to a di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligent enquiry and ſearching after her, that ſo ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving found her, they might goe, and ſell all, to buy her, that they might deny themſelues and their owne carnall wiſedome; that they might renounce the world, lightly eſteeming of tranſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tory pleaſures, profits, and preferments, the worlds three minions and darlings, and all, to purchaſe the pearle of true perfection, a pearle moſt precious and of ineſtimable value. Which now ſhineth and giveth a bright luſter in the mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litant Church by grace: but hereafter ſhall bee more admirably poliſhed and adorned by glorie in the tryumphant Church, in heaven, in the Kingdome of God, in that Kingdome, whereof, according to St. <hi>Auguſtine,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Aug. Marcel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>no epiſt. <hi>5.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>The King is Veritie, The Law is Charitie, the meaſure is Eternitie.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:13754:6" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. II.</hi> The Etymologie of Perfection.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">P</seg>Erfection is in Latine <hi>perfectio,</hi> and this from the verbe <hi>perficere,</hi> compounded of <hi>per</hi> and <hi>facere;</hi> and it ſignifieth to doe a thing throughly and abſolutely, to make a thing compleate and entire without de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect. Perfection in the Greeke is <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> from <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, which is derived from <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, an end: be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe in all things agible our underſtanding firſt intendeth and propoundeth the end, and then deliberateth of the moſt apt and direct meanes tending to that end; which being found out and put in execution, the deſired end is attained, and the worke perfected: whereupon this kinde of end is called the <hi>end of perfection,</hi> by way of ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellencie to diſtinguiſh it from the end of priva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, conſumption, or terme. And thus accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the ſenſe of the word both in the Greeke and Latine tongue, we ſay, <hi>Natura facit,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> 
                  <hi>doctrina dirigit, vſus perficit,</hi> nature frameth, doctrine and inſtruction directeth, and uſe or practiſe per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fecteth.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:13754:7" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. III.</hi> The divers kindes of Perfection.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">P</seg>Erfection primarily and originally be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longeth to God the fountaine there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, in whom is all vertue, grace, glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, excellencie, after a moſt perfect, infinite and incomprehenſible manner, therefore he onely is <hi>ſimpliciter &amp; abſolutè perfectus;</hi> ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply and abſolutely perfect. All perfection found in Angels, or men, or any creature, is from God by communicating, participating of his perfecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: and ſo are ſaid to be perfect, <hi>ſecundùm quid &amp; in ſuo genere,</hi> in ſome reſpects after their ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall kindes.</p>
               <p>Now (to omitte tranſcendentall perfection of metaphyſicall ſpeculation) this derivative parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipated perfection, really found in the creatures is of three ſorts, <hi>naturall, morall, ſpirituall.</hi> In naturall ſcience the Philoſopher deſcribeth per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection in the concrete or ſubject, ſaying, <hi>perfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctum ideſt,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Ariſt. de caelo lib. <hi>1.</hi> cap. <hi>4.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>extra quod nihil eorum qua ipſius ſunt, accipi potest.</hi> That is perfect to which nothing is wanting, of thoſe things which belong unto it. That is; which lacketh nothing requiſite either in the firſt, or ſecond moment of nature, nothing belonging to the eſſentiall parts, or naturall pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perties and qualities flowing from them.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Morall perfection,</hi> according to humane mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ralitie, is attained by the practice of intellectuall
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:13754:7" rendition="simple:additions"/>and morall vertues, and is called by the philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pher in his <hi>Ethickes,</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, that is, felicitie or happineſſe, which he ſaith is, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. That is,<note place="margin">Ariſt. Eth. <hi>1.6</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>The operation of the ſoule according to the beſt and perfecteſt vertue in a perfect life.</hi> Naturall perfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction in the creature is from God as author of nature. Morall perfection is acquired by fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent actions, according to the rules of humane Philoſophie.</p>
               <p>But Spirituall perfection is from God as the doner and giver of grace, and fountaine of all good. For, <hi>every good gift,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Iam. 1.17.</note> 
                  <hi>and every perfect gift is from above, and commeth downe from the Father of Lights.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. IIII.</hi> Of Spirituall Perfection.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>Pirituall perfection, is that precious pearle which God beſtowed on man in the ſtate of innocencie, with which he doth in rich and endow the Saints now in the ſtate of grace, where-withall, he will adorne them more abundantly in the ſtate of glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie.</p>
               <p>When the Lord God created <hi>Adam</hi> and ſaid,<note place="margin">Gen. 1.26.</note> 
                  <hi>Let us make man in our image after our likeneſſe:</hi> man ſo created was perfect, not onely by perfection of nature, but alſo of grace, of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riginall
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:13754:8" rendition="simple:additions"/>righteouſneſſe eſſentiall to the integritie of nature. He had a ſingular light of underſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to apprehend things eaſily, clearely, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out error, obſcuritie, difficultie, yea that which is more obſervable: when God brought <hi>Eve</hi> newly created vnto <hi>Adam,</hi> He ſaid of her pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plietically, this is now bone <hi>of my bones and fleſh of my fleſh,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Gen. 2.13.</note> 
                  <hi>ſhe ſhall be called woman, becauſe ſhe was taken out of man.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In the will of <hi>Adam</hi> was ſeated originall righteouſneſſe, the cornucopia or treaſurie of all vertues. In his affections reſided a perfect loue of God, and vertue, with a perfect delight in them. And it is rightly obſerved, that the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of the world was honoured of God in Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>radiſe with three eminent priviledges, 1. <hi>In intel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lectu, non errandi.</hi> 2. <hi>In voluntate, non peccandi.</hi> 3. <hi>In corpore, non moriendi.</hi> That is; with the pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viledge of not erring in his underſtanding; with the priviledge of not ſinning in his will; with the priviledge of not dying in his body. Such digni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie and excellencie had man in his creation, that his underſtanding was without error, his will without prevarication and obliquitie; and ſo con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuing, his body was to be immortall,<note place="margin">Aug. Enchir. ad Laur. cap. <hi>105.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>immortali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate minore,</hi> as S<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. <hi>Augustine</hi> ſpeakes, by a leſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſer and inferiour immortalitie in that earthly pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>radiſe, where feeding on the tree of life he might renew his ſtrength as the eagle, and never dye. Theſe things conſidered, it is no marvaile, if the ſweete Singer of <hi>Iſrael</hi> in admiration hereof cry out:<note place="margin">Pſal. 8.4.</note> 
                  <hi>What is man, that thou art mindfull of him?
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:13754:8" rendition="simple:additions"/>And the Sonne of man that thou viſitest him? For thou haſt made him a little lower then the Angels, and haſt crowned him with glorie and honour.</hi> Thus man created in the jmage and after the likenes of God, was glorious and perfect, untill hee tranſgreſſed that one command of his creatour. And this the Lord himſelfe, in expreſſe termes intimates by his Prophet <hi>Ezekiel</hi> ſaying,<note place="margin">Ezek. 23.</note> 
                  <hi>thou waſt perfect in thy wayes from the day thou waſt created untill iniquitie was found in thee.</hi> Which the Preacher of <hi>Ieruſalem</hi> explicateth in other words ſaying, <hi>Lee this have I found,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Eccles. 7.29.</note> 
                  <hi>that God made man upright, but they have ſought out many inventions.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. V.</hi> Of Perfection in the ſtate of grace.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Dam</hi> by tranſgreſſion having depri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved himſelfe, and his poſteritie of that excellent perfection, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with he was endowed in the ſtate of integritie; it remaineth, that wee now ſearch after ſuch ſpirituall perfection as may be found here in the militant Church in the ſtate of grace, expecting and hoping to have the ſame refined hereafter with a more eminent perfection in the ſtate of glory. That there is a ſpirituall per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection attaineable in this life is evident: by that command of Chriſt, <hi>Be yee therefore perfect,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Mat 5.48.</note> 
                  <hi>even
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:13754:9" rendition="simple:additions"/>as your Father which is in heaven is perfect.</hi> Saint <hi>Paul</hi> exhorteth the <hi>Hebrewes</hi> hereunto <hi>Therefore leaving the principles of the doctrine of Chriſt,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Heb. 6.1.</note> 
                  <hi>let us goe on unto perfection, &amp;c</hi> And there be perfect ones in the Church, as the ſame A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle plainly inſinuateth ſaying, <hi>Howbeit wee ſpeake wiſedome amongſt them that are perfect.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1 Cor. 2.6.</note> And againe, <hi>Let us therefore as many as be perfect, be thus minded.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Philip. 3.15.</note> This ſpirituall perfection attain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able in this life is the perfection of grace. And grace is a divine light flowing downe from God into the ſoule; diſplaying the beames thereof in the powers and faculties of the ſoule, enlightning them with diverſe vertues.</p>
               <p>Now though this perfection of grace be of very large extent, yet may it ſummarily be com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehended in theſe three things. Firſt in know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, ſecondly in righteouſneſſe, thirdly in per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeverance. For knowledge perfecteth the under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding righteouſneſſe and perſeverance per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fecteth the will.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="chapter">
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:13754:9" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. VI.</hi> Of Knowledge.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>N the ſoule of man there is a double power to receiue knowledge. Firſt, <hi>Naturall,</hi> to apprehend and know things within the compaſſe of na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture. The ſecond, <hi>Obedientiall,</hi> which being actuated by grace, is apt to appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hend and know things aboue, and beyond the cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuit of nature. From the firſt ariſeth naturall knowledge: from the ſecond ſupernaturall know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge. Naturall knowledge is but an handmaid, waiting and attending on knowledge ſupernatu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall, which after an eminent manner beautifieth and adorneth the underſtanding.</p>
               <p>Now as well-being ſuppoſeth a being, and grace ſuppoſeth nature; ſo ſupernaturall know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge findeth man furniſhed with ſome know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of things naturall, before his converſion to God, but this knowledge cannot perfect the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding of man with ſpirituall perfection.</p>
               <p>In the Cimmerian darkneſſe of heatheniſh ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norance, ſome were famous profeſſors and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mirers of knowledge attained by the light of na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture; who by laborious ſpeculations and indu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrious practiſe and obſervation, made great im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proovement of the common notions, and law of nature left in man. Such were the Prieſts of <hi>Ae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gypt,</hi> the <hi>Druides</hi> of <hi>Germanie,</hi> the <hi>Gymnoſophistae</hi>
                  <pb n="10" facs="tcp:13754:10" rendition="simple:additions"/>of <hi>India,</hi> the <hi>Magi</hi> of <hi>Perſia,</hi> and the Philoſophers of <hi>Greece,</hi> who were eminent aboue the reſt; a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt theſe were <hi>Socrates, Plato</hi> and <hi>Ariſtotle,</hi> and <hi>Pythagoras</hi> of <hi>Samos,</hi> of whom <hi>Marcus Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>relius</hi> noteth, that at the gates of his ſchoole was a ſtone, whereon he wrote theſe ſentences: <hi>He that knoweth not,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> Aurel. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <hi>9.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>that he ought to know, is a brute beaſt amongst men. He that knoweth no more, then he hath need of, is a man amongst brute beaſts. He that knoweth all that may be knowne, is a God a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongst men.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Now theſe great Maſters of humane ſcience walked in the owle-light of naturall knowledge onely, of whom the Trumpet of grace ſaith, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>;<note place="margin">Rom. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>profeſſing themſelues to be wiſe, they became fooles.</hi> Who ſo much ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mired of them as <hi>Socrates? Plato</hi> deemed him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe happie for being borne in his time: and the <hi>Athenians</hi> doiſied him after his death; yet from him came that prophane Apophthegme, <hi>Quod ſupra nos nihil ad nos; that which is aboue us doth nothing pertaine unto us.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Laſt. div. in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>it. li. <hi>3.</hi> ca. <hi>20.</hi>
                  </note> This <hi>Lactantius</hi> in de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtation thereof obſerved in his divine inſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Salomon</hi> in the knowledge of nature ſurpaſſed all the Sages among the Gentiles, for by a ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gular and extraordinary gift from God, he was wiſer than all men; as the Holy Ghoſt witneſſeth in theſe words.<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> 9. &amp;c.</note> 
                  <hi>And God gaue Salomon wiſedome and underſtanding exceeding much, and largeneſſe of heart, even as the ſand that is on the Sea-ſhoare. And Salomons wiſedome excelled the wiſedome of
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:13754:10" rendition="simple:additions"/>all the children of the Eaſt Countrie, and all the wiſedome of Aegypt. For he was wiſer than all men: than Ethan the Ezrahite, and Heman, and Chalcol, and Darda the ſonnes of Mahol.</hi> And verſ. 33. <hi>He ſpake of trees from the Cedar tree that is in Lebanon, even unto the Hyſſop that ſpringeth out of the wall. He ſpake alſo of beaſts, and of foule, and of creeping things, and of fiſhes.</hi> Such, ſo great was the wiſedome of <hi>Salomon</hi> in the knowledge of nature!</p>
               <p>But we conceiue <hi>Adam</hi> to haue excelled <hi>Salo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon</hi> and other men in largeneſſe, in certaintie, in conſtancy of knowledge, both by reaſon of his naturall endowments by creation; and alſo by reaſon of his long experience; for he had indeed (as <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> ſpeaketh) <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>,<note place="margin">Ariſt. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <hi>12.</hi>
                  </note> that eye of experience acquired by means of his long age, amounting <hi>to nine hundred and thirtie yeares.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Gen. 5</note> But now there be many things that hinder us, and make us deſpaire of attaining ſo great know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, and they be eſpecially fiue: Firſt weaknes of body. Secondly, ſhortnes of life. Thirdly, want of things neceſſary. Fourthly, perturbati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of affections. Fiftly and laſtly, temptations by evill Angells.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="chapter">
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:13754:11" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. VII.</hi> Of Knowledge ſupernaturall.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Lthough humane knowledge may ſerue as an handmaid to divine: al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though it may whet the underſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, and make it more acute and ſharpe; and enlarge it for the ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſion of things of an higher nature, yet can it not perfect it. Onely ſupernaturall knowledge addeth true perfection to the minde. The author or inſpirer hereof is <hi>God,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Iob 32.8.</note> for, <hi>the inſpiration of the almightie giveth underſtanding.</hi> The object there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of is <hi>Holy things,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Prov. 9.10.</note> for, <hi>The knowledge of holy things is underſtanding.</hi> Such knowledge commeth to man either by vertue of ſome extraordinary ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pernaturall light, as in old time by dreames and viſions and immediate inſpiration, to the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets and Apoſtles and holy men of God, or, as ordinarily now it doth, by divine revelation out of the canonicall Scriptures, through operation of the Spirit and Miniſtery of the Church. For <hi>Chriſt</hi> aſcending upon high, <hi>gaue gifts unto men;</hi> and as it is written,<note place="margin">Epheſ. 4.11.</note> 
                  <hi>He gaue ſome Apoſtles; and ſome Prophets; and ſome Evangeliſts; and ſome Paſtors and Teachers: for the perfecting of the Saints, for the worke of the miniſterie, for the edi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fying of the body of Chriſt: till wee all come into the unitie of the faith, and of the knowledge of the ſonne of God, unto a perfect man, unto the meaſure of the ſtature of the fulneſſe of Chriſt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="13" facs="tcp:13754:11" rendition="simple:additions"/>
The divine Oracles teach us to know two things, that we may be perfect according to the ſtate of this life. Firſt, <hi>God,</hi> ſecondly, <hi>our ſelues.</hi> God that we may beleeue in him, loue him and enjoy him. Our ſelues, that we may feare God and ſerue him in humility, and this humility cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth perfection, as St. <hi>Bernard</hi> intimateth in his thirty-ſeventh Sermon upon the <hi>Canticles.</hi> Now there are two degrees of knowing God: the firſt is to know him <hi>quantum cognoſcibilis eſt,</hi> ſo much and ſo farre as he can be knowne. Secondly, <hi>quantum nos ejus cognoſcitivi ſumus,</hi> to know him ſo much and ſo farre as we are able to know him.</p>
               <p>In the firſt degree, God onely knoweth him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe. <hi>Quideſt Deus? quod ad univerſum ſpectat, finis eſt. Quod ad electionem, ſalus; quod ad ſe, ip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe novit,</hi> ſaith St. <hi>Bernard. What is God?</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Bern. de con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſid. ad Eug. li. <hi>5.</hi> ca. <hi>11.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>to the world he is the end, to the elect, ſalvation; what he is to himſelfe, he himſelfe knowes.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Man a finite creature cannot poſſibly compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hend Him, who is infinite and incomprehenſible. For ſuch apprehenſion is <hi>ſupra modum receptivi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatis ſuae, aboue the meaſure and modell of his capa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citie.</hi> Wee cannot come to know God <hi>à priori,</hi> by the cauſe, for he onely is <hi>abſolutus à cauſa;</hi> ſeeing he is <hi>cauſa cauſarum, the cauſe of all other cauſes;</hi> all other depend on him, but he onely is independent, and before all other. But we may come to the knowledge of God <hi>à poſteriori</hi> by his workes and effects. Therefore he ſaid unto <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, thou ſhalt ſee my backe parts,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Exod. 33.23.</note> 
                  <hi>but my face ſhall not be ſeene.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="14" facs="tcp:13754:12" rendition="simple:additions"/>
Now we attaine to the knowledge of GOD fiue wayes.<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>jo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>r m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>in Re. cap. <hi>1.</hi>
                  </note> Firſt, by naturall reaſon; for as the Orator obſerveth, there is no Nation ſo ſavage or barbarous, which doth not acknowledge a GOD, Nature dictating this unto them. Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, by conſideration of the creatures, for herein is <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, as it is written, that <hi>which may be knowne of God is manifeſt in them,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Rom. 1.19.</note> 
                  <hi>for God hath ſhewed it unto them.</hi> Thirdly, by work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of miracles, for he onely can produce an ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect aboue the power of Nature; as the ſweet ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger of <hi>Iſrael</hi> noteth,<note place="margin">Pſal. 72.18.</note> 
                  <hi>Bleſſed be the Lord God, even the God of Iſrael, which onely doth wondrous things.</hi> Fourthly, God maketh himſelfe knowne unto us by infuſion of grace, enlightning us with the knowledge of him by his Spirit; for it is written, <hi>The Spirit ſearcheth all things,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1. Cor. 2.10.</note> 
                  <hi>even <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, the deepe things of God.</hi> Laſtly, by divinerevela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion out of the canonicall Scriptures, which are the mouth of God, ſpeaking unto man. There he makes himſelfe knowne, that he is the creator of all things, that he is moſt good and gracious, that he is loving to every man, and that his mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy is over all his workes. There we reade thoſe words of joy and conſolation, which are ſo plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant to our taſte, yea ſweeter than honey or the honey-combe. St. <hi>Ambroſe</hi> raviſht with the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light he found in the greene gardens of the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, ſaith,<note place="margin">Amb. ep. <hi>31.</hi> lib. <hi>4.</hi> ep.</note> 
                  <hi>Nunc deambulat in paradiſo Deus cum divinas ſcripturas lego, When I reade the divine Scriptures, God is walking up and downe in para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſe.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="chapter">
               <pb n="15" facs="tcp:13754:12" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. VIII.</hi> Of the Knowledge of God by affection, and not bare apprehenſion onely.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">B</seg>Y the heavenly Oracles in GODS Booke, we learne to know that GOD is one in nature and eſſence, but three in perſonall ſubſiſtence; The Father, the Sonne, the Holy Ghoſt. And they are di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinguiſhed by perſonall properties, called <hi>opera quoad intra,</hi> the inward workes of the bleſſed Trinitie; So the Father begetteth, the Sonne is begotten, the Holy Ghoſt proceedeth from them both. We diſtinguiſh them alſo <hi>per opera quoad extra,</hi> by their outward workes, when wee ſay, the Father createth, the Sonne redeemeth, the Holy Ghoſt ſanctifieth. Although to ſpeake properly, all outward workes extending to the creatures are wrought by all the three perſons, but after a different manner of working.</p>
               <p>All this theologicall knowledge of God may be found in them who are altogether imperfect. For it is not the knowledge of bare apprehenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, which addeth true ſpirituall perfection to the ſoule; for this is to be found in evill Angells and wicked men. But it is the knowledge of affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and affiance;<note place="margin">Bern. de con ſid. li. <hi>5.</hi> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>a. <hi>3</hi>
                  </note> or as Saint <hi>Bernard</hi> ſpeakes the <hi>knowledge of faith</hi> whereby we beleeue in God, loue him, and delight in him. In which ſenſe our Saviour ſaith, <hi>This is eternall life,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Iohn 17.3.</note> 
                  <hi>that they might
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:13754:13" rendition="simple:additions"/>know thee the onely true God, and Ieſus Chriſt whom thou haſt ſent.</hi> And the Evangelicall Prophet <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſay</hi> prophecying of Chriſt:<note place="margin">Eſay 53.11.</note> 
                  <hi>By his knowledge ſhall my righteous ſervant juſtifie many, for he ſhall beare their iniquities.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. IX.</hi> Of the knowledge of God in Chriſt.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>Rom the precedent diſcourſe, we learn by the teſtimony of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> and the Prophet <hi>Eſay,</hi> that the moſt excellent knowledge of God tending to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection and ſalvation, is to know him in Chriſt Ieſus. To wit, that God was in <hi>Chriſt</hi> reconciling the world unto himſelfe, not imputing their treſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſes unto them. Here we ſee God not as a law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giver upon his throne of Iuſtice, propounding unto us the covenant of works, but as a Saviour ſitting on the mercy-ſear, making with us a new covenant, the covenant of grace and peace in <hi>Chriſt.</hi> This knowledge is the very life of our ſoules, and joy of our hearts; which conſtrai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned the Trumpet of grace to ſay,<note place="margin">I halip. 3.8.</note> 
                  <hi>Yea doubtleſſe, and I count all things but loſſe, for the excellency of the knowledge of Chriſt Ieſus my Lord.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>We do behold the glory of the Deitie through the vaile of <hi>Christs</hi> humanitie;<note place="margin">Col. 2.9.</note> for <hi>in him dwelleth all the fulneſſe of the Godhead bodily.</hi> Therefore ſaid <hi>Chriſt</hi> to <hi>Philip,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Iohn 14.9.</note> 
                  <hi>He that hath ſeene mee hath
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:13754:13" rendition="simple:additions"/>ſeene the Father:</hi> and he himſelfe giues the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon hereof in another place, ſaying;<note place="margin">Iohn 10.30. <hi>Aug. in Pſal.</hi> 138.</note> 
                  <hi>I and the Father are one.</hi> Hence is it that St. <hi>Auguſtine</hi> ſaith, <hi>Lucerna ſapientiae caro Chriſti, the fleſh of Chriſt is the lanterne of wiſedome.</hi> And doeſt thou now O ſorrowfull ſinner deſire to know thy Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour Ieſus, to finde him out and ſee him, whom thy ſoule loueth and ſo longeth after? Behold he is in the flowrie gardens of the Scriptures, <hi>Ibi paſcit, ibi cubat in meridie,</hi> there he feedes, there he reſts at noone day; there he ſhewes himſelfe the ſame yeſterday, and to day, and for ever. From thence he graciouſly invites thee to ſeeke him, and calleth unto thee, ſaying,<note place="margin">Iohn 5.39.</note> 
                  <hi>Search the Scriptures, for in them you thinke to haue eternall life, and they are they which teſtifie of me.</hi> As if he ſhould haue ſaid, O yee careleſſe children, O yee fooliſh ones, why wander yee in the crooked paths of ſinne and death, why rather come yee not unto mee? If yee would not erre, loe I am the way; if yee would not be deceived, loe I am the truth; if yee would not die, behold, I am the life.</p>
               <p>For, <hi>I am the way th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> truth, and the life.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Iohn 14.6.</hi> Aug. in Ioan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tract. <hi>22.</hi>
                  </note>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Noneſt quò eas niſi ad me, non eſt quà eas niſi per me, there is no whither for you to goe but unto me, there is no way for you to goe by but by me.</hi> O come unto me then, <hi>Come unto me all yee that labour, and are heavie laden, and I will giue you reſt. Take my yoke upon you, and learne of me; for I am meeke and lowly in heart: and yee ſhall finde reſt unto your ſoules. For my yoke is eaſie and my burden is light.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="chapter">
               <pb n="18" facs="tcp:13754:14" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. X.</hi> Chriſts Incarnation.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>Eeing <hi>Chriſt</hi> doth ſo graciouſly invite and call us to him, let us earneſtly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire to know him that we may be u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nited to him, and made conformable to his image, and ſo perfected in him. For as St. <hi>Auguſtine</hi> ſaith;<note place="margin">Aug. in prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fat. in Pſal. <hi>54.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Chriſtus perfectio noſtra eſt, in illo enim perficimur, quoniam ipſius capitis membra ſumus: Chriſt is our perfection: In him we are per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect, becauſe we are members of him the head.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Now the firſt thing we are to know concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning our Saviour <hi>Ieſus Chriſt,</hi> is his Incarnation, or aſſuming of our nature in the wombe of the Virgin.</p>
               <p>Which St. <hi>Ambroſe</hi> calleth <hi>Sacramentum incar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nationis,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Amb. in Sym<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bot.</note> 
                  <hi>the Sacrament of his Incarnation:</hi> the firſt viſible foundation of our redemption. A myſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie kept ſecret, and hidden from the world, from men and Angells, untill it was revealed to the bleſſed Virgin <hi>Marie</hi> by the meſſage of an An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gell. And then the Eagle ſoaring upon high could ſay,<note place="margin">Iohn 1.14.</note> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, and <hi>the Word was made fleſh:</hi> And the trumpet of grace proclaiming the great myſterie of godlineſſe, beginnes with <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>God was manifeſted in the fleſh.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1 Tim. 3.16.</note> Thus the Sonne of God by nature, voluntarily and graciouſly became the ſonne of man; that the ſonnes of men might in him become the ſons of God by grace.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="19" facs="tcp:13754:14" rendition="simple:additions"/>
In this moſt myſterious worke of <hi>Chriſts</hi> in car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation, St. <hi>Bernard</hi> obſerveth,<note place="margin">Bern. de con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſid. li. <hi>5.</hi> c. <hi>9.</hi>
                  </note> that as in GOD there are three <hi>perſons and one eſſence,</hi> ſo by a moſt <hi>convenient contrarietie,</hi> there be in <hi>Chriſt three eſſences and one perſon.</hi> Which three eſſences are his reaſonable ſoule, his humane fleſh, his Deitie. Now the two former <hi>eſſences</hi> make up the hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane nature in <hi>Chriſt;</hi> for although there be <hi>three eſſences,</hi> yet are there but two natures. And though there be two natures, yet is there but one perſon, and not two, as <hi>Neſtorius</hi> the hereticke taught. Now although the humane nature in <hi>Chriſt,</hi> be not a perſon, yet is it individually and numerically diſtinguiſhed from the particular humane nature in <hi>Moſes</hi> and <hi>Peter,</hi> and each o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther man. But it is <hi>individnum extraordinarium, it is an extraordinarie individuall humane nature,</hi> which never had any ſubſiſtence in it ſelfe or for it ſelfe, but <hi>in divino ſuppoſito,</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>in the Word, in the Sonne of God.</hi> And it is an extraor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary individuall humane nature, becauſe alto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether without ſinne. Firſt, without originall ſinne, which is propagated from <hi>Adam</hi> by the Father; but our Saviour had no ſuch earthly Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and conſequently no originall ſinne. Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, without actuall ſinne; in that the humane nature in the firſt moment of conception, was by Hypoſtaticall union of the Deitie perfectly ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctified, &amp; made <hi>impeccabilis</hi> free from any power or poſſibilitie of ſinning. Hence by way of ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellency, he is that ſonne of man,<note place="margin">2 Cor. 3.28.</note> 
                  <hi>who knew no ſinne.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="20" facs="tcp:13754:15" rendition="simple:additions"/>
Now our bleſſed Saviour in regard of his two natures, was <hi>medius inter Deum &amp; hominem, a meane betwixt God and man,</hi> as participating of both: but a Mediatour, in reſpect of his office of reconciliation and redemption. For there is one <hi>God and one Mediatour betwixt God and men,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1 Tim. 2.5.</note> 
                  <hi>the man Chriſt Ieſus.</hi> And it is to be obſerved that the Apoſtle, ſaith not <hi>God,</hi> but the <hi>man Chriſt Ieſus.</hi> For God could not die, unleſſe he had been man: But God was made man, that he might die for man, and ſo reconcile man unto God. Hereup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,<note place="margin">Fulgent. ſerm. de dupl. nativ. Domini.</note> 
                  <hi>Fulgentius</hi> ſaith; <hi>Conceptus in utero, factus eſt particeps mortis noſtrae, being conceived in the wombe, he was made partaker of death with us.</hi> And Saint <hi>Auguſtine</hi> to the ſame purpoſe ſaith,<note place="margin">Aug. in Pſal. <hi>148.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Accepit exte, unde moreretur prote: He tooke that of thee, wherein he might die for thee.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="11" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XI.</hi> Chriſts Paſſion.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>INNE according to St. <hi>Iohns</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcription is <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>,<note place="margin">1 Iohn 3.4.</note> 
                  <hi>a tranſgreſſion of the Law,</hi> a privation of righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe commanded therein. Now a privation is <hi>minimae entitatis ſed maximae efficaciae, of the leaſt entitie, but of the greateſt efficacie.</hi> Which is moſt true in ſinne: For what was there in the whole world, in hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven or earth that could cauſe the death of the Son
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:13754:15" rendition="simple:additions"/>of God; or as St. <hi>Auguſtine</hi> ſpeakes, <hi>Vt aeternus moreretur: that he who is eternall ſhould die,</hi> but onely ſinne? And that not his owne, but ours; our prophaneneſſe, our crueltie, pride, luxurie, covetouſneſſe, intemperance, our lies, our oaths, our innumerable ſinnes.</p>
               <p>All which were made his, not by inherence, but by imputation. And he tooke them all upon him not <hi>ſubjectivè,</hi> but <hi>expiativè,</hi> not ſubjectiue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, but by way of expiation, to ſatisfie the juſtice, and appeaſe the wrath of his Father for them. For by ſhedding his bloud on the Croſſe for our ſinnes, he cancelled the fearefull bond, and <hi>put out the hand-writing againſt us.</hi> And ſo, as the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle teſtifieth, <hi>in him haue we redemption through his bloud, even the forgiueneſſe of our ſinnes,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Epheſ. 1.7.</note> 
                  <hi>accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the riches of his grace.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Our moſt gracious Saviour in that bitter ago<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie of his moſt dolorous paſſion upon the Croſſe, might well complaine with <hi>Ieremie</hi> the ſonne of <hi>Hilkiah, Behold and ſee,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Lam. 1.12.</note> 
                  <hi>if there be any ſorrow like unto my ſorrow.</hi> And may not all that by faith embrace him crucified on the Croſſe moſt truely ſay, behold and ſee, if there be any loue like unto his loue, who ſo loved us that he laid downe his life for us; who ſo loved us that he gaue himſelfe for us? Here is loue without meaſure; unparalleled charitie without any example.<note place="margin">Iohn 15.13.</note> 
                  <hi>Greater loue hath no man than this, that a man lay downe his life for his friends.</hi> Yea but the loue of Ieſus exceeded the loue of men, it paſſed the loue of <hi>Damon</hi> and <hi>Pythias,</hi> of <hi>David</hi> and <hi>Ionathan,</hi> it ſurpaſſed the
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:13754:16" rendition="simple:additions"/>loue of women. For as the choſen veſſell of mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy noteth, <hi>God commendeth his loue towards us, in that while wee were yet ſinners Chriſt dyed for us,</hi> Rom. 5.8. and in the tenth verſe following more emphatically he intimateth, that when wee were <hi>enemies, we were reconciled unto God by the death of his Sonne, much more being reconciled, wee ſhall be ſaved by his life.</hi> O moſt wonderfull death! O moſt meritorious work of <hi>ſupenerogation,</hi> where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in ſtands our righteouſneſſe and everlaſting ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation! O moſt happie death, bringing to man eternall life! <hi>Mors Chriſti, mors eſt meae mortis, quoniam ille mortuus eſt ut ego viverem,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Bernard. ad Milit.rem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pl. cap. <hi>11.</hi>
                  </note> ſaith holy <hi>Bernard: The death of Chriſt, is the death of my death, for he dyed that I might live.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="12" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XII.</hi> Chriſts Reſurrection.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">L</seg>Et us now paſſe from the Croſſe of our Lord Ieſus, and walke unto his ſepulcher in the garden of <hi>Io<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſſeph</hi> of <hi>Arimathea,</hi> and ſee whether his moſt ſacred body be there. But loe we haue the voice of an Angell telling us, <hi>He is not here,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Math. 28.6.</note> 
                  <hi>for he is riſen.</hi> Here our bleſſed Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viours reſurrection is proclaimed by an Herald from Heaven, by an Angell. Whereby we know that he is a perfect Mediatour betwixt God and us, <hi>tam merito quàm efficaciâ</hi> as well by the merit
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:13754:16" rendition="simple:additions"/>of his paſſion, as by the power and efficacy of his reſurrection. Satan the Serpent thought he had ſtrangled the fruit of our redemption by procu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring that ignominious and ſhamefull death of Chriſt on the Croſſe: ſuppoſing to haue kept him under the chaines of darkneſſe.<note place="margin">Aug. ſerm. <hi>1.</hi> in feſt. aſcenſ.</note> But as St. <hi>Augu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtine</hi> writeth, <hi>Muſcipula Diaboli crux Christi, eſca quâ caperetur, mors Chriſti, the Croſſe of Chriſt was the Devills trap, the baite whereby he was ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken; was the death of Chriſt.</hi> So the deceiver was deceived, the ſubtile Serpent was beguiled: for it was not poſſible, that he ſhould keepe him un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der death, who is the Lord of life,<note place="margin">John 11.25.</note> 
                  <hi>who is the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection and the life.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And therefore as by the will of the Father,<note place="margin">Rom. 4.25.</note> 
                  <hi>He was delivered to death for our ſinnes, ſo he was alſo raiſed againe for our juſtification.</hi> Here you ſee that our moſt gracious and mightie Redeemer was as <hi>Gorran</hi> ſaith, <hi>Pugil in morte, victor in reſurrectio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Gorran. in Ro. cap. <hi>1.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>a Champion in his death, a conquerour in his re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection.</hi> For now He triumphed over the graue and death: declaring to the world, to men and Angells, that he was perfectly juſt: otherwiſe he could never haue riſen unto Glory, had he beene uncleane, had he beene any way polluted and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>filed with ſinne; for into the heavenly <hi>Ieruſfalem</hi> ſuch ſhall in no wiſe enter. Yea, He roſe againe for our juſtification, to ſhew himſelfe a juſtifier of all that beleeue in him; to ſhew that he had ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken away their ſinnes, the wages wherof is death; that ſo they might at the laſt day riſe againe unto eternall life.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="24" facs="tcp:13754:17" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <hi>The reſurrection and glorification of our Lord Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Auguſt. deſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rect. dom. &amp; Cant. Alle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lujah.</note> 
                  <hi>according to St.</hi> Auſtine, doe ſhew what life we are to receiue, when he ſhall come to ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der <hi>digna dignis,</hi> evill to the evill and good to the good: then all the members of his myſticall bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy ſhall riſe up in Him their head, and ſo liue ever with him:<note place="margin">Fulgent. ſerm. de dupl. nativ. Chriſti.</note> for as <hi>Fulgentius</hi> ſaith, <hi>Reſurgens è ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulcro fecit nos participes vitae ſuae, by riſing out of the ſepulchre, He made us partakers of his life.</hi> And we know as the Scripture teacheth us,<note place="margin">2 Cor. 4.14.</note> that, <hi>He who raiſed the Lord Ieſus, ſhall raiſe up us alſo by Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus. And when Chriſt,<note place="margin">Coloſſ. 3.4.</note> who is our life ſhall appeare, then ſhall we appeare alſo with Him in glorie.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="13" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XIII.</hi> Chriſts Interceſſion.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hen the ſonne of God had ſuffered his moſt dolorous and bitter agony on the Altar of the Croſſe; when he had victoriouſly triumphed o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver the graue in his moſt glorious reſurrection: He aſcended upon high, and led cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tivity captiue, and is ſet on the right hand of God, continually making interceſſion for us: there he ever preſents unto the Father his humane nature, wherein He died and roſe againe, and performed ſo great things for us: there we ſinners haue an <hi>Advocate with the Father,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1 Iohn 2.1.</note> 
                  <hi>even Ieſus Chriſt the righteous, and he is the propitiation for our ſinnes:</hi>
                  <pb n="25" facs="tcp:13754:17" rendition="simple:additions"/>whereupon St. <hi>Auguſtine</hi> ſaith,<note place="margin">Aug. in Pſal. <hi>94.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Sacerdotem ſi re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiras ſupra caelos eſt, interpellat prote, qui in terra mortuus eſt prote: if thou require a Prieſt, He is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue the Heavens; He maketh interceſſion for thee who on earth died for thee. Who ſhall lay any thing to the charge of Gods Elect? it is God that juſtifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, who is he that condemneth?</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Rom. 8. v. 33.34.</note> 
                  <hi>it is Chriſt that died, yea that is riſen agaìne, who is even at the right hand of God, who alſo maketh interceſſion for us.</hi> What greater comfort and conſolation haue we in our pilgrimage, than to know and beleeue that the Lord Ieſus is our moſt faithfull Advo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate, who intercedeth for us day and night? who as St. <hi>Ambroſe</hi> ſpeakes,<note place="margin">Amh. in. ca. <hi>8.</hi> ad Rom.</note> 
                  <hi>Semper cauſas agit noſtras apud patrem, perpetnally pleades our cauſes before the Father.</hi> Who as the Apoſtle ſaith, <hi>maketh in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terceſſion for the Saints according to the will of God.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>He onely intercedeth for all Saints, and none of all the Saints intercede for him. So he is our onely true, perfect Mediatour. He intercedes with the Father for us, <hi>merito ſuo,</hi> by vertue of his owne merit. The Saints on earth intercede for others, but <hi>merito Chriſti,</hi> through Chriſts merit; for all their holy requeſts for others, all their pious interceſſions are offered upon the Golden Altar, and doe ſweetly aſcend up unto the throne of grace,<note place="margin">Apoc. 8.3.</note> 
                  <hi>per Ieſum Chriſtum Dominum noſtrum,</hi> through Ieſus Chriſt our Lord.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="14" type="chapter">
               <pb n="26" facs="tcp:13754:18" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XIIII.</hi> Our union with Chriſt.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hat will it availe us to know the merit of <hi>Chriſts</hi> death, the power of his re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection, the benefit of his interceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, unleſſe we participate of ſo great bleſſings? But participate of them wee cannot, unleſſe we haue communion with <hi>Christ,</hi> unleſſe we be of him and in him, as the branches are in the Vine, unleſſe we be members of his bodie, fleſh of his fleſh, and bone of his bones. And this is a great myſterie concerning <hi>Chriſt</hi> and the Church:<note place="margin">Eph. 5.32.</note> which to underſtand in ſome meaſure is moſt neceſſary, but to haue a ſpirituall ſenſe and feeling of it, is even an unſpeakeable foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine of joy and conſolation.</p>
               <p>As we are of and in <hi>Adam</hi> by nature; ſo are we of and in <hi>Chriſt</hi> by grace. And <hi>Christ</hi> who can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be had by portions, is whole in the whole Church, and whole in every faithfull member of the Church. And thus he communicates him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe unto us by his Spirit, for the ſame Spirit which giveth life unto the Head, quickeneth and enliveneth the members alſo; for if any haue not the <hi>Spirit of Chriſt,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Rom. 8.9</note> 
                  <hi>he is none of his:</hi> and therefore in <hi>Iohn</hi> 14.19. he ſaith to his Apoſtle, <hi>Becauſe I liue, yee ſhall line alſo.</hi> And all this proceeds from our union with him, which he inſinuateth in the twentieth verſe following; <hi>At that day ſhall yee
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:13754:18" rendition="simple:additions"/>know, that I am in my Father, and you in me, and I in you.</hi> This holy Spirit whereby wee are united to <hi>Chriſt,</hi> is the ſeede whereby we are borne of God, and the ſonnes of God. Becauſe <hi>yee are ſonnes,</hi> ſaith the Apoſtle, <hi>God hath ſent the Spirit of his Sonne into your hearts, crying Abba Father.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Obſcuro.</note> For our ſpirituall ſubſiſting in <hi>Christ</hi> is corre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpondent to his perſonalitie and ſubſiſtence, whereby he is the Sonne of God; So in him we alſo are the ſonnes of God; He is ſuch by nature, we onely through him by adoption and grace.</p>
               <p>Hence is it that St. <hi>Peter</hi> ſaith, <hi>We are partakers of the divine nature,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">2 Pet. 1.4.</note> which is communicated to all the three ſubſiſtences in the bleſſed Trinitie; and conſequently to the Sonne, and in him to us. This <hi>Christ</hi> prayed for, and was heard in that he requeſted and deſired for the faithfull, in thoſe words, <hi>That they all may be one, as thou Father art in me, and I in thee, that they alſo may be one in us.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Iohn 17.21</note> And St. <hi>Iohn</hi> intimateth as much, ſaying, <hi>Truely our fellowſhip is with the Father, and with his Sonne Ieſus Chriſt.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1 Iohn. 2.3.</note>
               </p>
               <p>Entreating here of the union of the Church with <hi>Chriſt,</hi> I was drawne to ſpeake of our adop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion through <hi>Chriſt.</hi> For by one and the ſame Spirit we are adopted in <hi>Chriſt,</hi> and united unto him. He unites himſelfe to us by grace, we are u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nited to him by faith. And ſo the whole perſon of the faithfull is united to the whole perſon of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> firſt to his fleſh, then through his fleſh to the <hi>Word,</hi> which was made fleſh. And this uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on is wrought after a ſpirituall, not corporall
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:13754:19" rendition="simple:additions"/>manner; after a ſupernaturall, not after a natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall manner. And therefore difficult to under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand, and hard to utter. But by this union wee are in <hi>Chriſt,</hi> and <hi>Chriſt</hi> in us, we liue in <hi>Chriſt,</hi> and <hi>Chriſt</hi> in us, we are made one with <hi>Chriſt,</hi> and <hi>Chriſt</hi> with us: that ſo by degrees we may be conformed unto him, firſt, by grace, after by glorie.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="15" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XV.</hi> Of the knowledge of our ſelues neceſſary to perfection.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He old precept in the ſchoole of the Grecian Philoſophers, may deſerue a due place amongſt us in the ſchoole of Chriſt, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>know thy ſelfe.</hi> For this knowledge is neceſſary unto perfection, and directeth us to it.<note place="margin">Plin. Nat. Hiſt. li. <hi>2.</hi> cap. <hi>1.</hi>
                  </note> Whereupon <hi>Plinie</hi> the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan cryes amaine, <hi>Furor profectò furor egredi &amp;c. tis madnes, tis madnes for a man to goe out of him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, and as if he knew all within, to prie and ſearch into all things without, as if he could meaſure any thing, who knowes not how to meaſure himſelfe.</hi> Now if thou wouldeſt wiſely meaſure thy ſelfe, take St. <hi>Bernards</hi> counſell, who adviſeth thee ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riouſly to conſider three things:<note place="margin">Bern. de con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſid. ad Eug. li. <hi>2.</hi> cap. <hi>4.</hi>
                  </note> firſt, <hi>Quid ſis,</hi> ſecondly, <hi>quis ſis,</hi> thirdly, <hi>qualis ſis;</hi> firſt, <hi>What thou art in regard of nature;</hi> ſecondly, <hi>who thou art. in reſpect of thy perſon;</hi> thirdly, <hi>What an one thou
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:13754:19" rendition="simple:additions"/>art in regard of thy manners.</hi> Wouldſt thou know what thou art by nature? I will not inſtruct thee out of the ſtore-houſe of nature; no, let God him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe teach thee, let him inſtruct thee out of Para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſe, ſaying, <hi>duſt thou art and to duſt ſhalt thou re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne.</hi> Here he who is α and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> tells thee thy be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning and thine ending, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>all is duſt;</hi> earth the meaneſt, the loweſt, the baſeſt of all the elements is predominant in tho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>: thou commeſt into the world clad with clay, with teares, and weeping mournfully; thou goeſt on with labour, and ſhame, irke ſomely, thou goeſt our with paine and anguiſh dreadfully; A wofull entrance, a miſerable continuance, a ſearfull Ca<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>aſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ophe.</p>
               <p>And wouldſt thou further underſtand what thy life is here on earth? Surely thy dayes are no better than <hi>Iacobs</hi> were, <hi>few and evill.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Gen. 47. v. 9.</note>
               </p>
               <p>And <hi>Ioh</hi> tells thee, that thou art of ſhort con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuance and full of trouble. The ſhortnes of thy life is ſuch, as <hi>David</hi> compares it to an hand bredth; St. <hi>Iames</hi> to a vapour; others to a ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow, to a dreame; or the dreame of a ſhadow; and nothing can be found ſo tranſitory to be a perfect Embleme of our ſhort continuance.<note place="margin">Wiſd. 5.9.</note> 
                  <hi>As ſoone as wee were borne, wee began to dram towards our end,</hi> ſaith the Wiſeman.<note place="margin">Ambr. de voc. gent. li. <hi>2.</hi> ca. <hi>8.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Nec priùs incipit au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geri atas noſtra, quàm minui; neither doth our age begin to increaſe, before it begin to decreaſe,</hi> ſaith St. <hi>Ambroſe.</hi> O then let us conſider, let us ſeri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly conſider, that this <hi>breve ſuſpirium,</hi> this ſhort ſigh, this momentanie life is <hi>momentum illud unde pendet eternitas, that moment whereon de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pends
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:13754:20" rendition="simple:additions"/>eternitie</hi> either eternall woe, or everlaſting felicitie. O thou creator of men, thou knoweſt our frame, thou remembreſt that we are but duſt; O teach us ſo to number our dayes, that we may applie our hearts unto wiſedome;</p>
               <p>Our life for the quantitie is vaine and momen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tanie; and for the qualitie thereof it is evill and full of trouble, afflicted with many perturbati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of minde, wi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> innumerable croſſes from our ſelues and from others, with infinte diſtractions and vexations of ſpirit. So that <hi>Scaliger</hi> might well ſay; <hi>Hominis vita non hac eſt, ſed via ad vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tam; this is not the life of man,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Scalig. exerc.</hi> 205. Sect. 2.</note> 
                  <hi>but the way unto life.</hi> Here is nothing but labour and ſhame and ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row; So that our life is indeede <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>a weake miſerable life, or rather no life,</hi> no time thereof is truely pleaſing and delight ſome to us.<note place="margin">Flor. Granat. parre <hi>1.</hi> cap. <hi>15.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Quod prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terijt, dolet; quod praeſens eſt affligit; quod futu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum eſt, turres: We ſigh and ſorrow for that which is paſt; we are afflicted and diſcontent with that which is preſent, and we are afraid of that which is to come.</hi> We are afraid to be unclothed, to put off our tabernacle of clay, to be reſolved into duſt;<note place="margin">Ariſt. Eth. <hi>3.</hi> cap. <hi>9.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>death is a thing moſt fear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full,</hi> ſaith <hi>Ariſtotle;</hi> this nature cannot brooke, <hi>abhorret à non eſſe, ſhee abhorres a not being;</hi> Grace may correct, but not change and take away na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture. <hi>Hoc habet humanus affectus; quoniam diligit vitam, odit mortem:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pet. Lombar. ſent. <hi>3.</hi> diſt. <hi>17</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>mans affection is ſuch, that he loveth life, and hateth death,</hi> ſaith <hi>Peter Lombard.</hi> Now conſider how many diſtempers from the elements, from our meats and drinkes are wee
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:13754:20" rendition="simple:additions"/>ſubject unto; how many caſuall accidents from evill Angells, and men, and other creatures are we daily expoſed unto, ſo that we haue cauſe per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petually to be in expectation of death, yea to complaine and cry out with the choſen veſſell of mercie; <hi>O wretched man that I am, who ſhall deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver me from the body of this death,</hi> Who (ſhall as <hi>Gorran</hi> gloſſeth upon it) deliver me <hi>à corpore hoc mortifero, ſamp; mortali,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Gorran. in</hi> Rom. 7.24.</note> 
                  <hi>ſub cujus dominio captivus ſum, in quo declino ad mortem naturae, per quod in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clinor ad mortem culpae; in quo horreo montem Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henna? Who ſhall deliver mee from this mortife<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous and mortall bodie, under whoſe dominion I am held captiue; wherein I decline to the death of na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, by which I am inclined to the death of ſinne; wherein I abhorre the death of Hell?</hi> Such, ſo va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riable and mutable, ſo tranſitorie and mortall is the ſtate of man, <hi>than whom,</hi> as <hi>Plinie</hi> notes,<note place="margin">Plin. not. hiſt. <hi>2.7.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing is more proud, and nothing more miſerable.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="16" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XVI.</hi> Of the further knowledge of our ſelues.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>Aving conſidered what thou art by nature; if thou wilt goe on to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection, thou muſt alſo conſider, who thou art in perſon, and what an one in qualitie. After our gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall calling of Chriſtianitie, there be many par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:13754:21" rendition="simple:additions"/>callings and ſtates of men both in Church and Common-weale, whereby they are diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſhed one from another; and hence ariſeth the diſtinction, and difference of the perſons of men; whereby they are obliged and bound to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme certmine offices, ſervices, and miniſteries for the good of others.</p>
               <p>Now thou muſt conſider what perſon thou art, whether a King, or a ſubordinate Magiſtrate, or an inferiour ſubject; whether a Biſhop or a Prieſt or a lay man; whether a Divine, or a Phyſitian, or a Lawyer, whether a Souldier, or a Merchant, or an artificer, or an husbandman, or a labourer, or whatſoever calling thou art of. And herein thou muſt employ thy endeavours to the glory of God, and the common good of men, following that excellent rule of St. <hi>Auguſtine;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Aug. in Ioan. tract. <hi>10.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Fac quicquid potes, pro perſona quam portas &amp; perficis, zelus do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus tuae comedit me; Doe what in thee lieth corre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpondent to the perſon thou ſuſtaineſt, and then thou doeſt perfectly performe that, the zeale of thy houſe hath eaten me up.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In the next place conſider what an one thou art, whether pious or prophane, cruell or merci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, humble or proud, covetous or liberall tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perate or intemperate: in a word, thou muſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider wherein thou doſt ſwarue from the rule of obedience, and tranſgreſſe <hi>Gods</hi> law. For <hi>niſi ad regulam,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Seneca ad Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cil. ep. <hi>11.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>pratia non couriges,</hi> ſaith <hi>Seneca: thou wilt not correct that which is amiſſe, but by the rule.</hi> But if thou ſtrictly examine thy ſelfe by that rule, it is to be feared, thou wilt finde thy ſelfe a great
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:13754:21" rendition="simple:additions"/>ſinner, a grievous ſinner, perhaps <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>out of meaſure ſinfull:</hi> thou wilt ſee thy prevarications und aberrations multiplied <hi>ſuper numerum,</hi> to be as <hi>David</hi> complained, <hi>innumera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, more than the haires of thy head.</hi> Oh, but the ſlnggiſh ſinner will not looke into that cleare glaſſe, to ſee his feſtered ſores, his otting corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting Uicers, leaſt the ſight thereof ſhould trouble and torment him For he thinkes it true which the Preacher ſaith, <hi>He that increaſeth knowledge,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Eccles. 1.18.</note> 
                  <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſeth ſorrow:</hi> which St. <hi>Ierome</hi> expounds thus,<note place="margin">Hieron. lib. <hi>2.</hi> adverſ. Pelag.</note> 
                  <hi>he underſtands that he wants perfection, and knowes by that which he doth know, how much it is which he doth not know.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But the carnall ſinner expounds it otherwiſe; by ſearching into the Law and the ſeverall bran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches of obedience therein contained, he diſcove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth the multitude of his ſinnes and tranſgreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and conſequently the guilt of many foule and monſtrous aberrations, for as that holy Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Fulgentius</hi> ſaith,<note place="margin">Fulgent. de gra. &amp; incarn. Dum. noſi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ſ. Chriſti.</note> 
                  <hi>Quantum ignorantta peccati minuitur, tantum reatus peccatorum augetur: as much as the ignorance of ſinne decreaſeth, ſo much the guilt of ſinne increaſeth.</hi> Now the guilt of ſinnes increaſeth the ſight of God, juſtice; and the extreame malediction, or curſe of the Law, cauſe remorſe of conſcience, &amp; increaſe ſorrow. But if this ſorrow be ſeaſoned and ſanctified with grace and faith in Chriſt Ieſus, it is not that ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row in morall Philoſophie, which is <hi>affectus de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructivus ſubjecti, an affection or paſſion deſtroying the ſubject;</hi> but it is <hi>affectus perfectivus &amp; ſalva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tivus
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:13754:22" rendition="simple:additions"/>ſubjecti, an affection perfecting &amp; preſerving the ſubject;</hi> for it is a pious, a profitable ſorrow, or as the Apoſtle ſpeakes,<note place="margin">2 Cor. 7.10.</note> 
                  <hi>a godly ſorrow which cauſeth repentance unto ſalvation not to be repented of.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="17" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XVII.</hi> Of righteouſneſſe perfecting the will.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>N the day when <hi>Adam</hi> was created, he was perfect in his underſtanding and will, but by diſobedience he be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came imperfect in both, and ſo was caſt out of that earthly Paradiſe. Now unleſſe we be renewed in <hi>Chriſt</hi> after the image of God, and regaine ſuch or greater per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection than <hi>Adam</hi> had in ſcience and ſanctitie, in knowledge and righteouſneſſe, we ſhall never enter into the paradiſe of heaven.</p>
               <p>What knowledge is eſpecially neceſſary unto perfection is formerly diſcovered. So that in the next place it remaineth to enquire what righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe is requiſit to perfect us and prepare us for the kingdome of heaven. Which before we come to, let us ſtill remember, that as I intima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted heretofore, there is a double perfection com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>patible to man.</p>
               <p>The firſt is abſolute, proper to the glorified ones in the Church triumphant, and not to be found in any of the children of men, ſo long as
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:13754:22" rendition="simple:additions"/>they be here in earthly tabernacles and mortall bodies of clay.</p>
               <p>The ſecond, not abſolute, but correſpondent to the ſtate of this life; and this is that, which by all meanes wee muſt ſtriue and endeavour to at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine unto, whilſt we are members of the militant Church, whilſt we are as yet ſtrangers and pil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grims, and way-faring men on earth.</p>
               <p>This then premiſed, conſider we the righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, whereby we are perfected according to the ſtate of this preſent life. And it is two-fold, the firſt is the righteouſneſſe of another, but imputed unto us, called therefore <hi>imputed righteouſneſſe.</hi> The ſecond is our owne righteouſneſſe, which is wrought in us by God through the ſanctificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of his Spirit, called <hi>inherent righteouſneſſe.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And firſt we will treat of that righteouſneſſe which being without us is imputed unto us of God, and ſo made ours: otherwiſe we could ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver be perfect diſciples in the ſchoole of <hi>Christ.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="18" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XVIII.</hi> Of righteouſneſſe imputed.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He righteouſneſſe which is without us, and not our owne, but imputed unto us, as being the righteouſneſſe of ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, is the righteouſneſſe of Ieſus our Mediatour; now his righteouſneſſe is of two ſorts: firſt, the <hi>righteouſneſſe of his perſon,</hi> where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:13754:23" rendition="simple:additions"/>he himſelfe is clothed and adorned; ſecond<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, the <hi>rightouſneſſe of his merit,</hi> whereby he doth cloath and adorne us, poore, naked, miſerable ſinners, and that of his meere grace, free bountie and goodneſſe.</p>
               <p>The righteouſneſſe of <hi>Chriſts</hi> merit is that me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritorious obedience which in our nature he per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed for us, to appeaſe Gods wrath conceived againſt us for our ſinne, to ſatisfie his ſevere ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice: that wee being abſolved from ſinne by his death, might be reconciled unto God, and ſo be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come heires of eternall life. This meritorious righteouſneſſe of our bleſſed Saviour, without which we are altogether imperfect, is in it ſelfe moſt perfect: and it pleaſeth God to account it unto us as our righteouſneſſe, and to impute it unto us, as done by us. For <hi>Chriſt</hi> ſuſtaining and bearing all our perſons in his death, by the will and determinate counſell of the Father died for us all. So that, that righteouſneſſe which he per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed for us in our name, may not unfitly be ſaid to be ours as done by us. For as St. <hi>Gregory</hi> ſaith;<note place="margin">Greg. Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral. expoſ in Iob. lib. <hi>24.</hi> cap. <hi>7.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Iustitia noſtra dicitur, non quae ex noſtro no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtra est, ſed quae divina largitate fit noſtra; it is cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led our righteouſneſſe, not which is ours of our own, but which is made ours by Gods bountie.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>erem. 23.6.</note> And in this regard the ſonne of <hi>Hilkia</hi> by the ſpirit of prophecy might well entitle him, <hi>Iehovam juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiam nostram, the Lord our righteouſneſſe.</hi> And thus much the trumpet of grace proclaimeth,<note place="margin">1 Cor. 1.30.</note> tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching us that <hi>Ieſus <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>hriſt is of God made unto us wiſedome, and righteouſneſſe, and ſanctification, and redemption.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="19" type="chapter">
               <pb n="37" facs="tcp:13754:23" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XIX.</hi> Of imputed righteouſneſſe made ours by faith.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">G</seg>OD of his meere grace giues unto us the meritorious obedience of his Sonne, accounting it unto us as ours, and withall, by the ſame grace giues us faith to apprehend it and apply it to our ſelues. For by this hand of faith we claſpe and embrace, and lay faſt hold on <hi>Chriſts</hi> righteouſneſſe, and ſo make it ours. Now this faith is a principall beame of that grace which enlighteneth all the faculties of the reaſonable foule, and is partly in the underſtanding, and partly in the will; for it is not a bare aſſent given to the object, ſeeing that ſuch may be in evill Angels and reprobates; and in that ſenſe St. <hi>Iames</hi> ſaith,<note place="margin">Iam. 2.19.</note> 
                  <hi>Daemones credunt &amp; contremiſcunt, the devills beleeue and tremble.</hi> but it is<note n="*" place="margin">Or rather an affiance in Chriſt the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deemer for pardon of ſin, grounded on the promiſe of the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpell.</note> a fiduciall aſſent to the promiſe of ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving grace in Chriſt. And as it is an aſſent, it hath place in the underſtanding; as it is fiduciall, it hath place in the will. A bare aſſent to the ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject, is too ſlender a ſetting forth of the formall cauſe of juſtifying faith, and too weake to ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port that which is the life of a Chriſtian, who ſaith with the Apoſtle,<note place="margin">Galat. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> 20.</note> 
                  <hi>I liue by the faith of the Sonne of God, who loved me, and gaue himſelfe for me.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="38" facs="tcp:13754:24" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <hi>Cornelius</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Bitonto,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Corn. Bitont. apud Whitak. Conc. ult.</note> upon the firſt to the <hi>Romans</hi> ſaith, that <hi>faith is not a bare credulitie, but a truſt and confidence, and includes ſome opera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the will.</hi> God indeed as the principall pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dominant, efficient cauſe worketh faith in man; this is the worke of God,<note place="margin">Iohn 6.29.</note> that <hi>wee beleeue on him whom he hath ſent:</hi> but man in whom faith is wrought, formally beleeveth, and that willing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, not againſt his will.<note place="margin">Aug. de Spir. &amp; lit. ca. <hi>34.</hi>
                  </note> All this St. <hi>Auguſtine</hi> plainely inſinuateth, ſaying, <hi>Voluntas, qua credi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus dono Dei tribuitur; the will whereby we beleeue is aſcribed to the gift of God.</hi> So then it is neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily inferred out of the precedent grounds, that both the will, and whole perſon of a Chriſtian is ſingularly perfected by the righteouſneſſe of faith in Chriſt Ieſus, whereby we, who were enemies, become well pleaſing, and acceptable to GOD: and therefore the choſen veſſell of mercy deſired this,<note place="margin">Philip. 3.9.</note> and onely this he deſired, that <hi>he might be foundin Chriſt, not having his owne righteouſneſſe, which is of the Law, but that which is through the faith of Christ, the righteouſneſſe which is of God through faith.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="20" type="chapter">
               <pb n="39" facs="tcp:13754:24" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XX.</hi> Of the different participating of impu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted righteouſneſſe by faith.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE righteouſneſſe of <hi>Chriſts merit,</hi> which is the materiall cauſe of our juſtification, is equally communica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to all that haue it; ſo that in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard of it, one is not more righteous than ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. For it is entirely imputed, unto whom it is imputed, and entirely embraced by all who par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticipate of it. But becauſe we apprehend and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply it to our ſelues by a ſpirituall inſtrument or organ, namely, faith; hence it co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>meth to paſſe, that all doe not equally apprehend and applie it to themſelues, for all haue not one degree or mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of faith. But it is according to one degree, in one, and according to another degree, in another, in ſome weaker, and in others ſtronger: and yet all haue true faith, and ſufficient to embrace Chriſts righteouſneſſe. For if we conſider faith <hi>ſecundùm rationem ſpecificam,</hi> in the eſſentiall forme, whereby it is ſpecified and differenced from other habits and vertues, ſo it is in all right beleevers alike; for every eſſentiall forme is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtituted in <hi>indiviſibili,</hi> and doth not admit lati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude, as not being capable of diviſion by more or leſſe. But if we conſider it <hi>ſecundùm rationem individualem,</hi> as it is inherent in divers ſubjects, ſo it is in ſome more, in others leſſe, and doth ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:13754:25" rendition="simple:additions"/>very great latitude. And ſo there may be one degree of faith in St. <hi>Peter</hi> another in St. <hi>Paul,</hi> and another in St. <hi>Luke,</hi> and another in <hi>Oneſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus.</hi> Hence was it that our Saviour ſaid to the <hi>Centurion</hi> in <hi>Capernaum,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Math. 10.8.</note> 
                  <hi>I haue not found ſo great faith, no not in Iſrael.</hi> And to the woman of <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naan, O woman great is thy faith!</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Math. 15.28.</note>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Aquinas</hi> aptly noteth,<note place="margin">Aqui. <hi>11.</hi> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ae. qu. <hi>112.</hi> art. <hi>4.</hi>
                  </note> that an habit is ſaid to be great two wayes; Firſt, <hi>in reſpect of the end and object, as being ordained to ſime greaet good;</hi> ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, <hi>in reſpect of the ſubject, which doth leſſe or more participate of the inherent habit.</hi> Now faith, as all other gifts and graces, comes downe from the Father of lights, and is diſpenſed and diſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buted to us by his Sonne,<note place="margin">Epheſ. 4.7.</note> 
                  <hi>for to every one is given grace according to the meaſure of the gift of Chriſt.</hi> So God is ſaid to <hi>deale to every ma the meaſure of faith</hi> Rom. 12.3. and in the fixt verſe following, <hi>He that prophecieth, muſt prophecy according to the proportion of faith.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Aqui. in Rom. cap. <hi>12.</hi> lect. <hi>1.</hi>
                  </note> Whereupon <hi>Aquinas</hi> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menteth, <hi>Nonſolùm alias gratias gratis datas dat Deus menſuratè, ſed etiam ipſam ſidem quae per di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lectionem operatur; God doth not onely giue by mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſura; other graces freely given, but alſo faith it ſelfe which worketh by loue.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Now although Almightie God doth giue un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to every man in his firſt converſion a certaine meaſure of faith: yet doth he not alwayes giue unto every man that full meaſure, which he ſhall after attaine unto; but he ſhall goe on from one degree to another, and ſtill receiue further in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe and improvement of his faith, untill that
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:13754:25" rendition="simple:additions"/>meaſure allotted him be accompliſhed. Eor even as plants when they firſt bud, and herbs in the garden, when they firſt put forth, are not adorned with that beautie, ſtature, and perfection, which they ſhall after haue; ſo neither are graces and vertues given of God to men at the firſt, ſuch, ſo great and perfect as afterward they ſhall be.<note place="margin">Ambr. de voc. gent. lib. <hi>2.</hi> cap. <hi>3.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mina chariſonatum plantae<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> virtutnus non in omni agrecordis humani totum hoc pariter quod futurae ſunt, naſcuntur; nec facilè reperitur in exordio ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turitas, &amp; in inchoatione perfectio. Exerit quidem frequenter potens &amp; miſericors Deus mir abiles iſtes ſuae operationis effectus &amp; quibuſdam menti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus, non expectatâ profectuum morâ, totum ſimul, quicquid collaturus eſt invehit: The ſeeds of gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces</hi> (ſaith St. <hi>Ambroſe</hi>) <hi>and plants of vertues, doe not in every field of mans heart ſpring up at the firſt, all that which they ſhall after be: neither is ripenes eaſily found in the beginning, and perfection at the firſt. God mightie and mercifull doth indeede oft<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times ſhew forth theſe wonderfull effects of his ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, and puts into ſome mindes, at once, all that he beſtoweth of them, not expecting any delay of pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficiencie.</hi> Thus ſome haue their proper meaſure of faith fully meaſured out unto them at the firſt, but others are to labour and pray for proficiencie to receiue further increaſe and augmentation of their faith, ſaying or rather praying with the bleſſed Apoſtles unto the Lord, <hi>increaſe our faith.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Luk. 9.5.</note> And with the Father of him that was poſſeſſed with the dumb ſpirit; <hi>Lord I beleeue,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Mark. 9. v. 24</note> 
                  <hi>helpe thou mine unbeliefe.</hi> This man beleeved, yet prayed
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:13754:26" rendition="simple:additions"/>he for decreaſe of unbeliefe; the Apoſtles belee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, yet prayed they to the Lord for increaſe of Faith. When as our gracious Saviour had ſpoken to his Apoſtles of his departure from them, and comming againe unto them he ſaith,<note place="margin">Joh. 14. v. 29.</note> 
                  <hi>and this haue I told you before it is come to paſſe, that when it is come to paſſe yee might beleeue.</hi> Now wee may not thinke that the Apoſtles beleeved not before, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe <hi>Chriſt</hi> ſaid that yee might beleeue; but as St. <hi>Auguſtine</hi> expounds it,<note place="margin">Aug. in Ioan. tract. <hi>79.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Creditur autem hoc non <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>de nova, ſedaucta: this is beleeved not by a new faith, but by ſaith increaſed.</hi> For in every vertue and conſequently in faith there be three things remarkable: Firſt, <hi>initium,</hi> ſecondly, <hi>incremen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum,</hi> thirdly, <hi>complementum.</hi> Firſt, <hi>the beginning,</hi> ſecondly, <hi>the growth or increaſe,</hi> thirdly, <hi>the ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and perfection.</hi> Faith is begun in ſpirituall babes or infants, growes and increaſeth in profi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cients, is full and perfect in men of ripe yeares, who dare boldly &amp; conſidently ſay, as it is writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten, <hi>Let us draw neere with a true heart in full aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance of faith,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Hebr. 10.22.</note> 
                  <hi>having our hearts ſprinkled from an evill conſcience, and our bodies waſhed with pure water.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="21" type="chapter">
               <pb n="43" facs="tcp:13754:26" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XXI.</hi> Of righteouſneſſe inherent, and firſt of righteouſneſſe according to mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall Philoſophie.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hat I may treat of this argument, with more perſpicuitie to be better under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood; it is not amiſſe to follow that old Pule, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, He that will teach well, muſt firſt looke into the names of thoſe things, whereof he treateth.<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>. Ariſt. Eth. <hi>2.</hi> cap. <hi>7.</hi>
                  </note> For ſeeing there are more things, than names, and conſequently many things without names; hence it co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>meth to paſſe, that there be many names equivocall, ſignifying more things than one, whereby the underſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding is apt to be deceived.</p>
               <p>Wherefore it is neceſſary to conſider what is meant by that righteouſneſſe, whereof I am now to ſpeake.</p>
               <p>In the ſchoole of humane philoſophie wee are taught; that there be three things in the ſoule, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, that is, <hi>paſſions, powers, habits.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Ariſt. eth. <hi>2.4</hi>
                  </note> Now it is not of paſſions, or powers, but of ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bits, that we are called vertuous or vicious, good or evill. And amongſt habits is ranked <hi>Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe,</hi> by which men worke righteouſneſſe, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiring and doing thoſe things that are juſt. And this is taken ambiguouſly, either for a particular vertue, or a generall; for a particular vertue, as
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:13754:27" rendition="simple:additions"/>when it is made one of the foure cardinall ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues, and ſo diſtinguiſhed from <hi>prudence, tempe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance,</hi> and <hi>fortitude:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Cicero Offic. <hi>1.</hi>
                  </note> as you haue it in the Ora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tour, and in St. <hi>Bernard,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Bern. de con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fid. ad Eug. li. <hi>1.</hi> cap. <hi>8.</hi>
                  </note> ſaying, <hi>Modum juſtitia quaerit, prudentia invenit, fortitudo vendicat, tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perantia poſſidet, juſtice ſeekes mediocritie, pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence findes it, fortitude challengeth it, temper ance poſſeſſeth it.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Otherwhile it is taken for a generall vertue, a panarie or cornucopia of vertues. Whereupon <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> ſaith,<note place="margin">Ariſt Eth. <hi>5.</hi> cap. <hi>3.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, it is not a particular kinde of vertue, but an uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſall vertue, according to that of <hi>Theognis;</hi>
                  <q>
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</q>
               </p>
               <p>In righteouſneſſe all vertue is ſummarily com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſed. The conſideration hereof mooved the Philoſopher to magnific it, and adorne it with that encomium,<note place="margin">Ariſt. Eth. <hi>5.</hi> cap. <hi>3.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Neither is the glorious evening ſtarre, nor <hi>Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifer</hi> the bright morning ſtarre, ſo wondered at and admired of men, as the vertue of righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe; which if wee could behold with mortall eyes, it would raviſh and bewitch us with the loue of it. So greatly, ſo highly did the pagan Philoſopher extoll the morall vertue of righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="22" type="chapter">
               <pb n="45" facs="tcp:13754:27" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XXII.</hi> How Chriſtian inherent righteouſneſſe differeth from morall righteouſneſſe.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">C</seg>Hriſtian righteouſneſſe excelleth mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall righteouſneſſe, as much as ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naturall things, things naturall, as heavenly things earthly, as the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit the fleſh.</p>
               <p>Morall righteouſneſſe co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>meth ſhort of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian inherent righteouſneſſe two wayes: Firſt, <hi>Quoad rectum principium;</hi> ſecondly, <hi>quoad debi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum finem:</hi> firſt, <hi>in reſpect of the procreant cauſe;</hi> ſecondly, <hi>in regard of the due end.</hi> Out of what fountaine flowes humane righteouſneſſe? Sure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly from humane inſtruction, humane motiues, meanes and induſtrie. But our inherent righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe flowes from GOD the onely fountaine of all true good, and is by him infuſed into our hearts through the powerfull operation of his ſanctifying Spirit. What was the end which the pagan Philoſophers aimed at, in the exerciſe of morall righteouſneſſe? Was it any other, than that of the vaine-glorious <hi>Phariſees</hi> in the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpell, the praiſe of men, and their owne glorie? But the end which we aime at in our good works is the true end, <hi>Finis ultimus &amp; ultimatus, the laſt end even Gods glory,</hi> the very butte and marke whereat we ſhoote the arrowes of all our pious endeavours and holy actions, according to that
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:13754:28" rendition="simple:additions"/>moſt excellent rule of the Apoſtle,<note place="margin">1 Cor. 10.31.</note> 
                  <hi>Whether yee eate or drinke or. what ſoever you doe, doe all to the glorie of God.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Againe, <hi>Chriſtian inherent right couſneſſe,</hi> is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tably diſtingniſhed from morall righteouſneſſe, for morall righteouſneſſe is acquired by many precedent acts of ventue, according to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Act les</hi> Rule;<note place="margin">Ariſt. Eth. li. <hi>2.</hi> cap. <hi>1.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, habits are gotten by ſemblable acts and operations. But in righteouſneſſe inherent it is farre other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe; for the habit is firſt infuſed of God, not acquired by man, or humane meanes; then from the habit ſo infuſed, flow many ſubſequent acts of righteouſneſſe, even all good workes. The man muſt be righteous before his worke be righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous; we muſt be <hi>arbaresy uſtitis,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Eſay 61.3.</note> 
                  <hi>trees of righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe,</hi> before wee can bring forth the fruits of righteouſneſſe:<note place="margin">Math. 7.17.</note> 
                  <hi>the good tree bringeth forth good fruit, but a corrupt tree emill fruit;</hi> from hence our Saviour inferres this concluſion, <hi>Wherefore by their fruits you ſhall know them.</hi> Now inherent righteouſneſſe complies with morall righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe in this, that it is ſome times taken for a par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioular vertue reſpecting onely our neigh bour, as the proper object thereof, and ſo the Apoſtle hath it, <hi>Tit.</hi> 2.12. where he ſaith; <hi>The Grace of God, that bringeth ſalvation, hath appeared to all men, teaohing us that denying ungodlineſſe, and worldly luſts, wee ſhould liue ſoberly, righteouſly, and godly in this preſent world.</hi> There righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe towards man is diſtinguiſhed from prery to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards God, and ſobrietie in our ſelues. Some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:13754:28" rendition="simple:additions"/>it is taken for a generall vertue, compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hending many vertues in it; ſo <hi>Moſes</hi> uſeth it, ſaying,<note place="margin">Deut. 6.25.</note> 
                  <hi>And it ſhall be our righteouſneſſe if wee ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue to doe all theſe Commandements, before the Lord our God, as He hath commanded us.</hi> Where righteouſneſſe hath for the proper adequate ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject thereof, <hi>God, man, and our ſelues.</hi> Thus St. <hi>Peter</hi> taketh it, after he had ſaid that <hi>God is no re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpecter perſons,</hi> he addes this prooſe:<note place="margin">Act. 10.35.</note> 
                  <hi>But in e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very Nation, he that feareth God and worketh righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe is accepted with him.</hi> So our bleſſed Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour ſeemes to take it,<note place="margin">Math. 6.33.</note> 
                  <hi>Secke yee firſt the kingdome of God, and the righteouſneſſe thereof</hi> and ſo St. <hi>Iohn, If yee know that he is righteous,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1 Ioh. 2. v. 29.</note> 
                  <hi>you know that we that dath righteouſneſſe is borne of him</hi> and in the ſame Epliſtle; <hi>He that doth righteouſneſſe, is righteous, as He is righteous.</hi> In this fenſe the Trumpet of grace te<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>eth the Law, the Law of righteouſneſſe, ſaying of the <hi>Iewes,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Rom. 9.31.</note> 
                  <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> Iſrael which followed after the Law of righteouſneſſe, hath not attained unto the Law of righteouſneſſe.</hi> So God by <hi>Ezechiel;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Ezech. 18.20</note> 
                  <hi>The righteouſneſſe of the righteous ſhall be upon him:</hi> and after ſpeaking of the refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med penitent, <hi>verſ.</hi> 22. <hi>In his rightenouſneſſe that he hath done he ſhall liue.</hi> Where he implies all duties of obedience injoyned in the Law to be the way unto life, according to that of <hi>Moſes,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Levit. 18.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> 
                  <hi>He that doth them, ſhall line in them.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="23" type="chapter">
               <pb n="48" facs="tcp:13754:29" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XXIII.</hi> Of the nature of inherent righteouſneſſe.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>S the will of man was depraved, and became imperfect through the loſſe of originall righteouſneſſe in the ſtate of innocency; ſo it muſt be in ſome meaſure perfected by inherent righteouſneſſe, beforeman be fitted and prepared to paſſe from the ſtare of grace unto the ſtate of glorie.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Inherent righteouſneſſe</hi> (called ſometimes by Divines <hi>regeneration,</hi> or <hi>renovation,</hi> or <hi>inchoation</hi> of a new life in us) is a ſupernaturall gift, and ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gular endowment powred into our hearts by God through the operation of his Spirit. And by meanes of this habituall endowment, wee are inclined and diſpoſed to doe well, to obey Gods will, to doe thoſe things that are juſt, to be fruit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full in good workes, and to worke all righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe. And ſo by degrees, we haue Gods image renewed in us, and put on the coate which <hi>Adam</hi> put off, for by this meanes, wee <hi>put on that new man which after God is created in right couſneſſe and true Holineſſe.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Epheſ. 4.24.</note> Now by this righteouſneſſe we are truely and really juſt though imperfectly, and it is called our owne righteouſneſſe to diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſh it from the imputed righteouſnes of Chriſt Ieſus, which is every way moſt perfect and ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolute. The choſen veſſell of mercie calls it our
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:13754:29" rendition="simple:additions"/>owne righteouſneſſe.<note place="margin">Zanch. in cap. <hi>3.</hi> ad Philop.</note> And this he doth as <hi>Zan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chic</hi> obſerveth for two cauſes. Firſt, becauſe it is really and truely infuſed into our hearts of God by his Spirit, and ſo is made ours. Secondly, becauſe the actions of pietie, equitie, tempe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, and all righteouſneſſe flowing from it are performed by us. For God by his grace giues us a will and deſire to ſerue him, and feare him, and to doe righteouſly, but it is we that will and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire, it is we that ſerue God, and feare him, and doe the workes of righteouſneſſe.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="24" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XXIIII.</hi> Of the fruit of inherent Iuſtice.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>F we would goe on ſtill unto perfecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, we muſt bring forth the fruit of inherent juſtice, we muſt walke in the way of actuall righteouſneſſe, and be ever found in the practiſe of vertue and exerciſe of good workes: we muſt not ſuffer the heaven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly fire, enkindled in our hearts, to goe out and die, but blow it up daily, by vertuous operations and actions.</p>
               <p>Habituall righteouſneſſe is that roote of grace, the branches whereof are holy deſires and endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours, and the fruits growing on them are good workes, wherein wee muſt labour to abound, that ſo as <hi>St. Peter</hi> ſaith,<note place="margin">2 Pet. 1.1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> 
                  <hi>An abundant entrance may be ministred unto us into the everlasting king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:13754:30" rendition="simple:additions"/>of our Lord and Savlour Ieſus Chriſt.</hi> Now as we ſee the Roſe growing on the branches, and crop it, for the fragrant ſmell, and other uſes, but the roote in the ground is hid, and wee ſee it not: So the roote of righteouſneſſe is hid in the heart, and ſeene onely of God, who onely is <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>the underſtander of the heart,</hi> before whom all things are naked and bare, even the thoughts of men and Angells; but the fruit of good workes is ſeene of men, and is profitable to the doers, and to them that ſee them. Yea by them we are declaratorily juſtified before men, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puted juſt in the judgement of the Church, as <hi>Zacharie</hi> and <hi>Elizabeth</hi> were in the Synagogue.<note place="margin">Act. 1.6.</note> For this cauſe our bleſſed Saviour ſtirreth up and exhorteth his Diſciples to the practiſe and exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe of good workes,<note place="margin">Math. 5.16.</note> ſaying unto them, <hi>Let your light ſo ſhine before men, that they may ſee your good workes, and glorifie your Father which is in hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>If wee be living branches, abiding in thetrue Vine, let us giue eare unto the Vine, ſaying unto us,<note place="margin">Joh. 15.7.5.8.</note> 
                  <hi>I am the Vine, and yee are the branches: He that abideth in me, and I in him, the ſame bringeth forth much fruit.</hi> And after, <hi>Herein is my Father glorified, that yee beare much fruit, ſo ſhall you be my Diſciples.</hi> Here <hi>Chriſt</hi> inſinuateth that if wee be in him, we muſt bring forth fruit, yea much fruit, many good workes, laying up in ſtore for our ſelues a good foundation againſt <hi>the time to come,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1 Tim. 6.18.</note> 
                  <hi>that we may lay hold on eternall life.</hi> We muſt not verbally only but really profeſſe <hi>Chriſt,</hi>
                  <pb n="51" facs="tcp:13754:30" rendition="simple:additions"/>we muſt not ſay, Lord, Lord, but doe what he bids us.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Marcus Aurelius</hi> obſerveth that the old <hi>Greekes</hi> were wont to ſpeake much,<note place="margin">Mar. Auret cap. <hi>8.</hi>
                  </note> and doe lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle; but the ancient <hi>Romanes</hi> were wont to ſpeake little and doe much. Let not us <hi>Christians</hi> be like the talkatiue <hi>Grecians,</hi> but the actiue <hi>Romanes,</hi> let not us be good ſpeakers, and ill doers, like unto the Philoſopher in <hi>Gellius,</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>,<note place="margin">A. Gell. li. <hi>17.</hi> cap. <hi>19.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>factis procul, verbis tenus, all words and no deeds,</hi> leaſt we be no better than the figge treegrowing betweene <hi>Hieruſalem</hi> and <hi>Bethany,</hi> which bare leaues and no fruit, and therefore was accurſed of <hi>Chriſt.</hi> It is not ſuitable to be called <hi>Chriſtians,</hi> and in our liues to imitate pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gans. <hi>Non ſufficit nobis nomen Chriſtianum,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Amb. in ſerm. de aſcen. Dom.</note> 
                  <hi>quod accepimus, ſi non opera bona Christiani fecerimus,</hi> ſaith St. <hi>Ambroſe, the name of Chriſtian, which we haue taken on us, is not ſufficient for us, unleſſe wee doe the good workes of a Chriſtian.</hi> What ſhall the name availe us without workes correſpondent? <hi>Nomenhabes, &amp; factum non habes,</hi> ſaith St. <hi>Augu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtine,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Aug. in <hi>1.</hi> ep. Ioan. c. <hi>3. v. 17</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>thou haſt the name, but not the deede;</hi> thou ſayeſt well and doeſt ill, thou weareſt <hi>Chriſts</hi> li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verie, and vaunteſt of the cogniſance of his name, but indeede thou ſerveſt Satan, and doeſt the workes of the Devill, and doeſt the workes of the Devill, and art unleſſe thou repent to be ranked amongſt thoſe miſerable, for lorne hypocrites, of whom St. <hi>Paul</hi> writes to the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop of <hi>Crete,</hi> ſaying, <hi>They profeſſe they know God,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Tit. 2.16.</note> 
                  <hi>but in workes they denie Him, being abhominable and diſobedient, and unto every good work reprobate.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="25" type="chapter">
               <pb n="52" facs="tcp:13754:31" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XXV.</hi> Of the nature and qualitie of good workes.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>Anuall Artiſts doe by a certaine rule trie and examine their worke, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther it be right or wrong; even ſo in Religion, wee trie and examine our morall actions by the Law of GOD as an infallible rule. If they erre from this rule, they are <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, tranſgreſſions, evill workes: if they accord with the rule, and are conforma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to the morall Law, they are ſo farre forth to be judged good workes. Now in a good worke, two things are remarkeable; firſt, as it is a worke; ſecondly, as it is good; for as it is a worke, it is from nature; as it is good, it is from grace: and as it is a good worke, both from nature and grace; and all from God, who is the onely author of nature, and doner of grace.</p>
               <p>God doth not onely giue us our being, and preſerue us in it, but ſupports and ſuſtaineth us by his concurrence in all our actions. For he as univerſall and ſupreme agent, hath his influence into all the actions and operations of inferiour a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gents, ſo that in him we both liue and moue and haue our being, and without him wee neither mooue nor worke, wee can doe nothing; yet in that by his concurrence wee immediatly doe this
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:13754:31" rendition="simple:additions"/>or that worke, it is ſaid to be from us; but if it betruely good, the goodneſſe of it is immediatly from Gods grace working in us, both to will it, and to doe it of his good pleaſure.</p>
               <p>We muſt alwayes lay this for a ground, that good workes muſt flow from the fountaine of faith, without which it is impoſſible to pleaſe GOD;
<q>
                     <l>Omne etenim pietatis opus,<note place="margin">Proſp. in E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pigram.</note> niſi ſemine recto exoritur fidei, peccatum est.</l>
                     <l>Everie pious worke is ſinne, if it grow not out of the right ſeede of faith.</l>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>In the next place wee are to conſider, that the goodneſſe of a morall act depends of two things: Firſt, the object; ſecondly, the circumſtances.<note place="margin">Pet. Soto de inſtit. ſac. part. <hi>2<hi rend="sup">•</hi>.</hi> lect. <hi>4<hi rend="sup">•</hi>.</hi>
                  </note> The object is ſome dutie of obedience comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded in the Law, the circumſtances are the end, time, place, &amp;c. but the chiefeſt is the end inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, for this according to <hi>Aquinas</hi> doth qualifie and ſpecifie the act, for <hi>actus exterior,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>informatur ex voluntate,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Aqui. in Rom. ca. <hi>14.</hi> lect. <hi>2<hi rend="sup">•</hi>. Rom. 2.14.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>the outward act is formed by the will,</hi> that is, intending ſuch an end. <hi>Now when the Gentiles, which haue not the Law, doe by nature the things conteined in the Law,</hi> their works are morally good in reſpect of the object. But becauſe they intend not Gods glorie, but their owne, they faile in the circumſtance, their inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion is evill, and conſequently their workes. Whereupon St. <hi>Auguſtine</hi> conſidering, that they neither proceeded of faith, nor aimed at the right end, remoues all goodneſſe from them, ſaying,<note place="margin">Aug. praeſas. in Pſal. <hi>31.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Vbi fides non erat, bonum opus non erat, bonum e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nim
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:13754:32" rendition="simple:additions"/>opus intentio facit, intentionem fides dirigit: where there was no faith, there was no good worke, for intention makes the worke good, and faith directs the intention.</hi> And after, <hi>Non valde aſpicias quid facit homo, ſed quid, cum facit, aſpiciat; Doe not greatly obſerue what a man doth, but what he aimeth at, when he doth it.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And indeed heathens and hypocrites doe good works, <hi>quoad genus operis,</hi> but not <hi>quoad intentio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem mandantis, they doe the worke conteined in the Law, but not according to the intention of the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mander,</hi> who intendeth his owne glorie. And ſo their workes, although they ſeeme glorious and ſpecious to men, yet are they but like an earthen pot guilded over, which ſeemes gold, and is not, or like grapes curiouſly painted on the wall which the birds flie to, but cannot feede on them. <hi>Sunt opera</hi> ſaith St. <hi>Auguſtine,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Aug. in Ioan. tract. <hi>25.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>quae videntur bona, ſine fide Chriſti, &amp; non ſunt bona, quia non referuntur ad eum finem ex quo ſunt bona; there be workes which ſeeme good without faith in Chriſt, and are not good, becauſe they are not referred to that end, whereby they are good.</hi> Hence is it that according to that trite and uſuall diſtinction both the works of pagans and hypocrites are deemed good <hi>ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sundùm ſubſtantiam actus, non ſecundùm modum requiſitum, in regard of the ſubſtance of the act, but not in regard of the manner requiſite to ſuch an act.</hi> For to honour their parents, to relieue the poore, and ſuch like, may be good in the ſubſtance of the act, and yet come ſhort in the circumſtance, and faile in the manner. Whereas we know that
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:13754:32" rendition="simple:additions"/>God lookes not ſo much to our doing, as to our well-doing, and as it hath beene obſerved by Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vines;<note place="margin">Flor. Granat. parte <hi>6.</hi> ca. <hi>4.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Deus non tam remunerat verba quàm adver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bia; God doth not ſo much reward verbs as adverbs, not ſo much doing, as well-doing;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Rom. <hi>2.7.</hi>
                  </note> for as the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle ſaith, <hi>He will render to them who by patient con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuance in well-doing, ſeeke for honour and glorie, and immortalitie eternall life.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Moſes</hi> ſaid unto the houſe of <hi>Iſraell,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Deut. 6.25.</note> it <hi>ſhall be our righteouſneſſe if we obſerue to doe all theſe Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandements before the Lord our God, as he hath commanded.</hi> Not onely that which he hath com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded us, but in ſuch manner as he hath com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded: For that which is good loſeth the beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie and glory of the goodneſſe of it, when it is not done after a good manner. Men ſpend a part of their life idely, doing nothing; another part care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſly, in doing that which concernes them not, and another part wickedly in doing ill. But wee that are <hi>Chriſtians</hi> muſt endeavour to ſpend all our dayes in doing well, and ſtriue to imitate our gracious Saviour, of whom it is ſaid,<note place="margin">Mark. 7.37.</note> 
                  <hi>He hath done all things well.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The ſonne of <hi>Amos</hi> exhorteth us to learne this leſſon, ſaying, <hi>Ceaſe to doe evill, learne to doe well.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Eſa. 1.16, 17.</note> And the Lord God himſelfe in the beginning of times ſaid unto <hi>Cain,</hi> the ſecond man in the world, <hi>If thou doeſt well, ſhalt not thou be accepted?</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Gen. 4.7.</note> 
                  <hi>if thou doeſt not well, ſinne lieth at the doore.</hi> O let us then be diligent in well-doing, painfull labou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers in <hi>Chriſts</hi> Vineyard; let us be fruitfull in good workes, committing the keeping of our
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:13754:33" rendition="simple:additions"/>ſoules unto God in well-doing, as unto a faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full creatour.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="26" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XXVI.</hi> That no man by his owne righteouſneſſe keepeth the Law, and is without ſinne.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He morall Law, is a rule of obedience, telling us what we ought to doe, not teaching us what we are able to doe. As long as wee are in this bodie of death, the remainder of the old <hi>Adam,</hi> the part unregenerate,<note place="margin">Galat. 5.17.</note> 
                  <hi>the fleſh fighteth againſt the Spirit, and the Spirit againſt the fleſh.</hi> So that wee cannot doe what we would; and conſequently wee can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not keepe the Law, as we would.</p>
               <p>Upon this unavoidable <hi>Suppoſition</hi> I may con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude, that it is a vaine and needleſſe ſpeculation, to diſpute of mans poſſibilitie to keepe the Law; and ſo to be without ſinne if he will. And thus much St. <hi>Hierome</hi> intimates,<note place="margin">Hieron. li. <hi>1<hi rend="sup">o</hi>.</hi> adv. Pelag.</note> 
                  <hi>Poſſe hominem eſſe ſine peccato, ſi velit, aut verum eſt aut falſum; ſi ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum eſt oſtende quis fuerit, ſi falſum eſt, quicquid falſum est, nunquam fieri poteſt:</hi> That is, <hi>for a man to be able to be without ſinne if he will, is either true or falſe, if it be true, ſhew who it is, if it be falſe, what ſoever is falſe can never be done.</hi> As if he had ſaid to <hi>Critobulus,</hi> either ſhew me a man that is with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out ſinne and keepeth the Law, or elſe your diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puting is <hi>de impoſſibili,</hi> of a thing impoſſible, and
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:13754:33" rendition="simple:additions"/>therefore vaine and frivolous. It is ſaid of no man but the man <hi>Chriſt Ieſus,</hi> who is alſo <hi>God,</hi> that he did all things well; that he did no ſinne;<note place="margin">Mar. 7.37. 1 Pet. 2.22.</note> in his mouth there was no guile. It was his incompara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble priviledge and unparalleled prerogatiue, to be <hi>agnus immaculatus, a Lambe without blemiſh, and without ſpot,</hi> as he is called by St. <hi>Peter.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1 Pet. 1.19.</note> As for us, we haue <hi>all gone aſtray like ſheepe,</hi> wee all haue beene as an uncleane thing, and all our righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe is as filthy ragges; and there is none juſt on earth that doth good and ſinneth not. God in the beginning inriched us with grace, and enabled us to doe his will; but wee by tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſion are become bankrupts, unable to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme our due obedience. So that when we looke our ſelues in the glaſſe of the Law, wee eſpie our manifold ſtaines and ſpots of ſinne, wee ſee our miſerable infirmity and diſability to good, which cauſeth us to implore the divine aide, and aſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance of grace. And indeede to this end, as St. <hi>Auguſtine</hi> notes, <hi>The Law was given,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Aug. de Sp. &amp; lit. ca. <hi>19.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>that grace might be ſought for; and grace was given, that the Law might be fulfilled:</hi> for it was not through the fault of the Law that it was not kept, but through the fault of the wiſdome of the fleſh; which fault, was to be revealed by the Law, and healed by grace. Whence wee gather, that,<note place="margin">Rom. 8.3.</note> that ſame <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, cap. <hi>8.</hi> verſ. <hi>3.</hi> doth accrew un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to it from us, <hi>in quo infrim abatur per carnem,</hi> in as much as it was weakened through the fleſh.</p>
               <p>So that during the combat of the Spirit and the fleſh, and the contrarietie of theſe two in us, <hi>poſito
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:13754:34" rendition="simple:additions"/>hoc,</hi> our condition being this, as the Apoſtle ſaith, <hi>Wee cannot doe the things we would;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Gal. 5.17.</note> but <hi>wee would</hi> keepe the Law,<note place="margin">Rom. 7.22.</note> for we delight in the Law of God after the <hi>inner man.</hi> Yet upon a new ſuppoſall of the impediment remooved, St. <hi>Auguſtine</hi> grants a poſſibilitie of keeping the Law,<note place="margin">Aug. de Sp. &amp; lit. ca. <hi>3.5.</hi>
                  </note> ſaying, <hi>Behold how that perfect righteouſneſſe is without example in men, and yet it is not impoſſible: for it might be, if ſo great a will was applied, as is ſufficient to ſo great a thing. And it would be ſo great, if we were ignorant of none of thoſe things which pertaine to righteouſneſſe, and thoſe things did ſo delight our minde, that, that delight did overcome whatſoever other impediment of pleaſure or ſorrow. Which that it is not ſo, it is not in reſpect of impoſſibilitie, but Gods judgement.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>So much St. <hi>Auguſtine</hi> grants, upon a ſuppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſall which by the judgement of God ſhall not be, and he ſaid a little before,<note place="margin">Aug. ubi ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pra.</note> 
                  <hi>Neminem tam perfectae juſtitiae in hac vita fuiſſe, veleſſe, vel futurum eſſe, that none in this life hath beene ſo perfectly righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, or is or ſhall be.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>When God gaue the Law in Mount <hi>Sinai,</hi> he knew mans weakneſſe, how unable he was to keepe it;<note place="margin">Bern. in Cant. ſerm. <hi>50.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Nec latuit praeceptorem, praecepti pondus hominum excedere vires, Neither was the Comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der ignorant, that the waight of his commandement exceeds the powers of men.</hi> But he did it to throw downe the wiſedome of the fleſh, which is an ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie to God and his Law; he did it to cauſe man to ſee his owne vileneſſe, his ſpirituall povertie and weakneſſe.<note place="margin">Bern. ubi ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pra.</note> For, <hi>Mandando impoſſibilia, non
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:13754:34" rendition="simple:additions"/>praevaricatores homines fecit, ſed humiles: by com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manding things impoſſible, he made not men ſinners but humble,</hi> ſaith St. <hi>Bernard.</hi> He thought it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hoouefull, that man ſhould be admoniſhed of his inſufficiency, that ſo he might ſeeke and thirſt af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter a Mediatour, that he might more ardently de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fire grace, by praying to him, who is all-ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent, who is nigh to all that call upon him, to all ſuch as call upon him faithfully.</p>
               <p>Gods commandements implie perfection, and he commands us to be perfect, but to this end, that wee ſeeing and acknowledging our owne wants and imperfections, may vehemently deſire to be perfected by his grace. And here wee are to obſerue that golden rule of St. <hi>Proſper,</hi> worthy to be obſerved of all.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>In Omnibus menitis Dei, at<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> mandatis,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Proſp. ep. ad Demet. ☜</note> 
                  <hi>una ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dem<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> ratio eſt &amp; divinae gratiae, &amp; humanaae abe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dientiae: nec ob aliud unquam datur praeceptum, ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſi ut quaeratur praecipientis auxilium: In all Gods admonitions and commands, there is one and the ſame reaſon, both of Gods grace and of mans obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence: neither is the commandement at any time gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven for any other thing, but that the helpe of him that commandeth may be ſought for.</hi> So much obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience, as the Law requireth of us, ſo much grace wee ſtand in need of, and this are wee to obtaine by prayer from him, who is the fountaine of grace. Wee and our Fathers haue done amiſſe, wee haue turned aſide, every one to his owne way; wee all haue ſinned, and come ſhort of the glory of God, and ſo all doe greatly ſtand in need
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:13754:35" rendition="simple:additions"/>of his grace.<note place="margin">Prov. 20.9. Iob 25.4.</note> Who can ſay, <hi>I haue made my heart cleane, I am pure from my ſinne? or how can he be cleane that is borne of a woman?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>We reade in holy Writ, that there was one <hi>Lot</hi> in <hi>Sodome,</hi> whoſe righteous ſoule they vexed with their uncleaneneſſe; of two amongſt all the thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſands in <hi>Iſrael,</hi> who were vouchſafed as worthy to enter into the land of <hi>Canaan,</hi> the land flowing with milke and honey, <hi>Ioſuah</hi> the ſonne of <hi>Nun,</hi> and <hi>Caleb</hi> the ſonne of <hi>Iephunnch,</hi> yea wee reade of three, who might deliver their owne ſoules from temporall judgements by their righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, <hi>Noah, Iob,</hi> and <hi>Daniel.</hi> Theſe and many o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther we reade of in holy Writ, who were righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous in mans judgement, and in Gods gracious ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptation: but we reade not that any one of them did perfectly keepe the Law, and was without ſinne.<note place="margin">Ambr. apol. <hi>1.</hi> David. ca. <hi>4.</hi>
                  </note> Whereupon St. <hi>Ambroſe</hi> ſaith; <hi>Da mihi aliquem ſine prolapſione delicti? Shew me any one without the fault of ſinne?</hi> Such an one would be a rare miracle, worthily to be admired of all. But alas! ſuch an one is like the mountaine of gold, or the Philoſophers ſtone, or the ſecond intenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons in <hi>Logicke,</hi> which haue no reall abſolute ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſtence; and indeede are nothing, ſaue onely in the theorie, and operation of the underſtanding: In ſcholaſticall ſpeculation, you may heare the noiſe of ſuch an one, but you ſhall not ſooner find him than the eccho in the Poet, <hi>Quem non inve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis uſquam, eſſe putes nuſquam,</hi> whom you finde not any where, you may ſuppoſe to be no where. For St. <hi>Hierome,</hi> averreth the truth when he ſaith,
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:13754:35" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <hi>Solus Deus eſt in quem peccatum non cadit,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Hiero. Dama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo, de prod. fl.</note> 
                  <hi>it is God onely, who is not ſubject to ſinne;</hi> in like manner, St. <hi>Bernard</hi> ſaith, <hi>Non peccare,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Bern. in Cant. ſerm. <hi>23.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Dei juſtitia eſt, ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minis juſtitia indulgentia Dei: not to ſinne is Gods righteouſneſſe, mans righteouſneſſe is Gods indul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gencie.</hi> So that we muſt all acknowledge our im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfection, wee muſt confeſſe with St. <hi>Iames, In many things, wee offend all.</hi> And with him that leaned on the breſt of our Saviour, drinking thence of the ſtreames of grace, with him alſo wee muſt comeſſe all, and ſay;<note place="margin">1 Iohn 1.8.</note> 
                  <hi>If wee ſay that wee haue no ſinne, wee deceiue our ſelues, and there is no truth in us.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="27" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XXVII.</hi> Of the growth and increaſe of inherent righteouſneſſe.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He vegetatiue facultie in man, after he is formed never ceaſeth to worke by augmenting and increaſing the bodie, untill it haue attained due dimenſions of length, bredth, and height, in that juſt quanti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, which is allotted as proper and peculiar to e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very particular man; whereby he is in that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect perfected. And this augmentatiue facultie, as <hi>Scaliger</hi> hath it, ceaſeth by Law of nature,<note place="margin">Exerc. <hi>282.</hi>
                  </note> the thirtieth yeare, leaſt ſhee ſhould affect infinitenes. For that was to uſurpe the prerogatiue of her
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:13754:36" rendition="simple:additions"/>Creator, who is <hi>natura naturans,</hi> the former and creator of nature, and who onely is actually in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finite.</p>
               <p>This juſt quantitie is not acquired at once, but by degrees; ſo we increaſe in our infancie, more in our child-hood, yet more in our youth, never ceaſing, untill we haue attained natures perfecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. In like manner, in the ſpirituall eſtate of the ſanctified regenerate man, there is a meaſure of perfection allotted to every particular man by God, which is not ordinarily given at once, but attained by degrees. Firſt, wee are infants, then proficients, and after perfect men in <hi>Chriſt.</hi> We are infants of what age ſoever we be, when wee are borne a new by the laver of regeneration: for then,<note place="margin">Barthol: Car. ſum. Concil. Concil. Vien.</note> as the councell of <hi>Vienna</hi> defineth, <hi>wee received informing grace and vertues infuſed in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of the habit, though not of uſe, in regard of the time.</hi> After that we beginne to produce thoſe ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bits in actuall exerciſing of righteouſneſſe, holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and other vertues, profiting and growing up into <hi>Chriſt</hi> who is the head; till at length by de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees we come unto a perfect man, unto the mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure <hi>of the ſtature of the fulneſſe of Chriſt.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Epheſ. 4.13.</note>
               </p>
               <p>Our bleſſed Saviour received the Spirit with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out meaſure:<note place="margin">John 3.34.</note> that He as the head might by the influence of grace convey and diſtill ſenſe and motion into all the members of his my ſticall bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die. But every member receiveth grace according to the <hi>meaſure of the gift of Chriſt.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Epheſ. 4.7.</note> Therefore whereas <hi>Chriſt</hi> received the <hi>Spirit</hi> without mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore,<note place="margin">Aug. in Ioan. tract. <hi>74.</hi>
                  </note> St. <hi>Auguſtine</hi> ſaith, <hi>Ceteris ad menſuram da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur,
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:13754:36" rendition="simple:additions"/>&amp; datus additur, donec unicui<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> pro modo ſuae perfectionis propria menſura compleatur: To the reſt he is given by meaſure, and being given, is increa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, untill every mans proper meaſure be fulfilled, according to the modell of his perfection.</hi> Now eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry mans proper meaſure of perfectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is unknown to him, and knowne onely to God: to the end that every one of us ſhould ſtriue and contend by all meanes to attaine it, here in obſerving that of the Greekes, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, aſpire to the higheſt, and thou ſhalt attaine a mediocritie, a meaſure befitting thee.</p>
               <p>Now this is not attained at once, but by de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees, <hi>Is qui ſummum locum aſcendere nititur, gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dibus, vel paſſibus, non autem ſaltibus elevatur: He</hi> (ſaith St. <hi>Gregorie</hi>) <hi>who ſtriues to aſcend up a most high place, is raiſed by degrees,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Greg. ep. l. <hi>9.</hi> ep. <hi>71.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>by ſteps and paces, not by jumpes and leapes.</hi> Wee muſt by lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle and little aſpire with the wings of prayer, and ardent deſire of perfection; and although all<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mightie God delay us and put us off, yet we muſt not giue him over, but importune him with the Widow in the Goſpell;<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Luke 18.</hi> ☜ Aug. in <hi>1.</hi> op. Ioan. <hi>3.</hi>
                  </note> for as St. <hi>Auguſtine</hi> excellently noteth, <hi>Deus differendo extendit de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderium, deſiderando extendit animum, extenden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>do facit capacem; God by differring us, extends the deſire, by deſiring, he enlargeth the minde and by enlarging it, He maketh it capable,</hi> that is, able to receiue ſuch a meaſure of perfection, as hee is pleaſed to giue us. And wee muſt with all dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence and devotion awaite the time when hee will be pleaſed to doe it. For as he doth not pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:13754:37" rendition="simple:additions"/>reward our workes with eternall life, but in due time: ſo ſaith <hi>Aquinas,</hi> he doth not <hi>pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently enercaſe grace,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Aqui. <hi>1<hi rend="sup">•</hi>. 2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>.</hi> qu. <hi>114.</hi> art. <hi>8.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>but in his time when wee ſhall be ſufficiently diſpoſed to the receiving of increaſe of grace.</hi> And for this (to uſe the Prophet <hi>Davids</hi> phraſe) <hi>ſhall every man that is godly pray unto him in a time when he may be found;</hi> which time, that we may find,<note place="margin">Luk. 18.1.</note> our Saviour directs us by a parable, teaching us, alwayes to pray, and not to faint. And hereunto the choſen veſſell of mercie exci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth us in that briefe exhortation,<note place="margin">1 Theſ. 5.17.</note> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>pray without ceaſing.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="28" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XXVIII.</hi> Of Spirituall ſloath an enemie to perfection.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>Pirituall ſloath in <hi>Chriſtians</hi> is a maine obſtacle to their growth in Chriſtia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, a mighty impediment hindering their proficiency in grace and vertue. For many are ſo ſtupified and benummed with a careleſſe negligence of their eſtate, that they paſſe on their daies from weeke to weeke, from month to month, and from yeare to yeare, never ſeri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly conſidering with themſelues, whether they grow better or worſe in their ſpirituall eſtate and courſe of vertue, whereas indeed nothing is more true, than that of old, <hi>Non progredi eſt regredi, not to goe forward, is to goe backward in the way of
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:13754:37" rendition="simple:additions"/>pietie.</hi> And ſurely he was never good, who doth not deſire and endeavour to be better; and he that endeavoureth not to be better, will ſoone grow worſe, ſoone learne to goe backward with the Crab-fiſh in <hi>Plinie: Profectò nolle proficere, defi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cere est, indeede to be unwilling to grow better,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Plin. nat. hiſt. lib. <hi>9.</hi> cap. <hi>31.</hi> Bern. ep. <hi>254.</hi> ad Garin.</note> 
                  <hi>is to grow worſe:</hi> with St. <hi>Bernard, Let us not delude and dereiue our ſelues,</hi> for as that holy Father tells us in the ſame place, <hi>inter profectum &amp; defectum in hoc ſtatu mortalis vitae nihil medium invemitur; In this ſtate of mortall life, there is no middle courſe betwixt proficiency and deficiency,</hi> betwixt going backward and going forward in grace. And there the ſame Father ſpeaking of the juſt and righteous ſaith;<note place="margin">Bernard. ub<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> ſuprà.</note> 
                  <hi>Iuſtus nunquam arbitratur ſe comprehendiſſe; nunquam dicitſatis eſt, ſed ſemper eſurit ſitit<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> juſtitiam; The juſt man never ſuppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth that he hath comprehended, never ſaith it is enough: but alwayes hungreth and thirſteth after righteouſneſſe.</hi> So that if he might liue alwayes, he would alwayes, as much as in him lieth, ſtriue to be more righteous. But as the emptieſt blad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders are moſt filled with winde, ſo the pooreſt <hi>Chriſtians</hi> haue many times the greateſt conceit and opinion of their own ſufficiency; they thinke they haue enough, when as in truth they haue a great deale too little. <hi>Omnia illi deſunt,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Bern. de con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſid. l. <hi>2.</hi> ca. <hi>7.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>qui nil ſibi deeſſe putat, he wants all things, who thinketh he wanteth nothing,</hi> ſaith holy <hi>Bernard.</hi> When our Saviour rehearſed the precepts of the ſecond Table to the young man; he anſwered preſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, <hi>All theſe things haue I kept from my youth up:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Mat. 19. v. 20, 21.</note>
                  <pb n="66" facs="tcp:13754:38" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <hi>what lacke I yet?</hi> but the wiſedome of GOD threw downe his pride, and ſtopped his mouth with a, <hi>Si vis eſſe perfectus, &amp;c. If thou wilt be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect, goe and ſell all that thou haſt, and giue to the poore, and thou ſhalt haue treaſure in heaven.</hi> This was a corroſiue to his ſtomach, a pill which he could not well digeſt. And yet there ought to be in every one of us ſuch a meaſure of perfection, as that through effectuall charitie, and loue of God, we ſhould be readie and willing upon juſt occaſion, actually to relinquiſh father and mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, wife and children, our goods, our lands, our liues, and all things, for the aſſerting of GODS glorie, and for the teſtimony of Ieſus. This hiſtorie of that young man in the Goſpell teacheth us, how forcible a <hi>remora</hi> the loue of the world and worldly things is, to ſtay the ſhippe of the Chriſtian ſoule, ſaying on in her voyage un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to perfection and felicitie. Whereupon the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle St. <hi>Iohn</hi> cryes amaine unto us,<note place="margin">1 Iohn 2.15.</note> 
                  <hi>Loue not the world, nor the things of the world, for if any man loue the world, the loue of the Father is not in him.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="29" type="chapter">
               <pb n="67" facs="tcp:13754:38" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XXIX.</hi> Of three evill qualities in ſpirituall ſloath.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Careleſſe negligence of our eſtate in pietie, is attended with three evill properties: Firſt, it is cold and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſe in proficiency; ſecondly, it is heavie and dull in going on to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection; thirdly, it is a waſter and deſtroyer of grace, and ſo a maine enemie to perfection: Wherefore this ſpirituall ſluggiſhneſſe is by <hi>Io<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hannes de ſancto Geminiano</hi> aptly compared to <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne,</hi> the higheſt planet, for three things: Firſt, He is <hi>infrigidativus,</hi> of a cold qualitie;<note place="margin">Ioan. de Sanct. Gem. de exem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pl. &amp; Simili<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> rerum. lib. <hi>1.</hi> cap. <hi>2.</hi>
                  </note> ſecond<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, He is <hi>tardè inceſſivus,</hi> of ſlow motion; third<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, He is <hi>faetuum mortificativus,</hi> a deſtroyer of young ones.</p>
               <p>Firſt, as <hi>Saturne</hi> is of a cold cooling qualitie, cauſing coldneſſe in the inferior bodies, and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citing melancholy: So ſpirituall ſloath makes a careleſſe Chriſtian become cold and remiſſe in charitie, in the loue of God and man; for he nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſo loveth GOD <hi>objectivè,</hi> as to will more good to Him than to any creature, neither doth he ſo loue Him <hi>appretiativè,</hi> as to value Him at a higher rate or price than the whole world, or his owne life; <hi>Nedum intenſivè,</hi> much leſſe doth he loue God with a greater and more ardent degree of loue, than his owne life or any other creature.
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:13754:39" rendition="simple:additions"/>And ſeeing the love of our neighbour is the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flection of Gods loue in out hearts, this being ſo remiſſe, that other of neceſſitie muſt be very coole, and ſo coole as that he neither loveth his neighbour as himſelfe, after the rule of the Law, nor as Chriſt loved us, which is the rule of the Goſpell. So that whereas inward perfection con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſts in the <hi>loue of God and our Neighbour,</hi> ſaith <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quinas,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Aquin. in Heb. cap. <hi>6.</hi> lect. <hi>1.</hi>
                  </note> the ſpirituall ſluggard muſt needs come ſhort of perfection, being ſo cold and defectiue in this golden vertue of <hi>Charitie,</hi> which is <hi>Vincu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lum perfectionis,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Col. 3.14.</note> 
                  <hi>the very bond of perfection.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Againe, as <hi>Saturne</hi> is of a ſlow motion, finiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his courſe through the <hi>Zodiacke</hi> in no leſſe than thirtie yeares: ſo the ſpirituall ſluggard, is very ſlow in the uſe of grace, and exerciſe of good workes, going ſo ſlowly on unto perfecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; as that he doth ſcarce <hi>formicinum gradum movere,</hi> mooue as faſt as the piſmire, and ſtands in neede to be brobd with <hi>Salomons</hi> goade, and ſet on his way with a <hi>Vade ad formicam piger &amp;c. Goe to the Ant thou ſluggard,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Prov. 6.6.</note> 
                  <hi>conſider her wayes and be wiſe: which having no guide, over-ſeer or ruler, provideth her meate in the ſummer, and gathereth her food in the harveſt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Laſtly, as <hi>Saturne</hi> is deſtructiue to young ones lately brought forth; ſo ſpirituall drowſineſſe and remiſſeneſſe even ſlay the fruits of grace and vertue, when they begin to ſpring up. If any pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous motions to good, be lately engendred in the heart, either by reading the word of life, or hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring it read, preached or expounded, or by pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:13754:39" rendition="simple:additions"/>admonition, or any good meanes, by and by this peſtilent vice is readie to ſtrangle them in the birth. Children borne under the dominion of <hi>Saturne,</hi> are not vitall, many times die within a few dayes, as the Aſtrologers ſay, ſo good mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions begunne in the ſpirituall ſluggard, oft die as ſoone as they be borne, and ſo never come to perfection. So that (whereas <hi>Fulgentius</hi> ſaith of <hi>Saturne, Filios verò ſuos comediſſe fertur;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Fulg. Myth. ad Catum. l. <hi>1.</hi> in Fab. Sat.</note> 
                  <hi>quòd quodcun<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> tempus gignit, conſumit;</hi> He is ſaid to devoure his ſonnes, becauſe <hi>whatſoever time be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>getteth, it conſumeth</hi>) this ſpirituall ſloath doth it not in a long tract of time, but in the nativitie or ſoone after; for this common pernicious vice is like the red <hi>Dragon</hi> in the <hi>Apocalyps,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Apoc. 12.4.</note> which ſtands before the woman readie to be delivered, for to devoure her childe as ſoone as it is borne. But wee muſt ſhake off this peſtiferous Viper, wee muſt be vigilant, and ſtand upon our watch every houre, leaſt whilſt wee ſleepe the enemie come, and ſow tares amongſt the good ſeeds of grace ſowen in our hearts. When the fire of the Spirit is begun to be enkindled in us, let us not quench it, and put it out againe with the cold wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of careleſſe remiſſeneſſe and negligence: but as the Trumpet of grace exhorteth, let us with all <hi>diligence and holy endeavour,</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>,<note place="margin">2 Tim. 1.6.</note> 
                  <hi>blow up the ſparkes of grace</hi> already ſparkling in our ſoules, let us by all meanes nouriſh them, but not extin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſh them, that ſo we may grow up into <hi>Christ</hi> our head, unto a perfect man, following the moſt wholeſome counſell of the great Apoſtle
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:13754:40" rendition="simple:additions"/>St. <hi>Peter,</hi> concluding his laſt Epiſtle with this heavenly exhortation, <hi>Grow in grace, and in the knowledge of our Lord and Saviour Ieſus Chriſt: to him be glorie both now and for ever, Amen.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="30" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XXX.</hi> What perfection of inherent righteouſneſſe is attainable in this life.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>Oſt abſolute and infinite perfecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of righteouſneſſe is onely in God, who is that light in whom there is no darkneſſe at all; of whom the ſweet ſinger of <hi>Iſrael</hi> could ſay,<note place="margin">Pſal. 145.17.</note> 
                  <hi>The Lord is righteous in all his wayes, and holy in all his workes.</hi> But that righteouſneſſe which is in man is finite and limi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, and ſuch is all the perfection he can attaine in it: and both accrew unto him by participati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, from him who is the fountaine of righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and perfection. Now that perfection com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>patible to man,<note place="margin">Aquin. in Phil. cap. <hi>3.</hi> lect. <hi>2.</hi>
                  </note> is two-fold, firſt, <hi>Viae,</hi> ſecondly, <hi>Patriae:</hi> the firſt incident to man in the ſtate of grace, whilſt he is as yet a way-faring pilgrim and ſtranger on earth: the ſecond belonging to man when he comes into his heavenly Country, and is a member of the triumphant Church in the ſtate of glorie. What perfection of righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe wee may attaine in the way of this life, wee are now to enquire of: and in ſearching it
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:13754:40" rendition="simple:additions"/>out, wee ſhall finde all our perfection attended with much imperfection. <hi>Haec hominibus ſola per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectio, ſi imperfectos eſſe ſe noverint:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Heron. adv. Peti. li. <hi>1<hi rend="sup">o</hi>.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>This is the onely perfection in men, if they acknowledge them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues imperfect.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But how ſhall we know and acknowledge our ſelues imperfect, but by finding out in our ſelues the defect and want of thoſe things whereby we ſhould be perfected? and by what other meanes can wee poſſibly be perfected, than by knowing God, and beleeving in God, and loving God, and obeying God For by ſuch knowledge, faith, charitie, and obedience, Chriſtian perfection is attained. But alas, as the Apoſtle ſaith,<note place="margin">1 Cor. 13.9.</note> 
                  <hi>wee know in part, and ſo wee beleeue in part, and loue God in part, and obey him in part.</hi> St. <hi>Gregorie</hi> therefore knits the foure linkes of this chaine, by the firſt and the laſt with a <hi>tantò quantò,</hi> ſaying, <hi>tantò quis operatur, quantò Deum noverit:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Greg. in Ezek. hom. <hi>22.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>ſo much as wee know God, ſo much wee obey him in our workes;</hi> ſuch as our knowledge is of him, ſuch is our obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience to him, ſuch is our righteouſneſſe; and hereupon St. <hi>Iohn</hi> ſaith, <hi>Hereby wee know,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1 Iohn 2.3.</note> 
                  <hi>that wee know him, if wee keepe his Commandements.</hi> Now wee cannot keepe his Commandements, unleſſe wee loue him, for <hi>this is the loue of God,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1 Ioh. 5. v. 3.</note> 
                  <hi>that wee keepe his Commandements;</hi> and wee can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not loue him, unleſſe we beleeue in Him,<note place="margin">Gal. 5.6.</note> 
                  <hi>for faith worketh by loue,</hi> and we cannot beleeue in Him, unleſſe wee know him, and can ſay with the Apoſtle, <hi>Scio cui credidi;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">2 Tim. 1.12.</note> 
                  <hi>I know whom I haue beleeved.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="72" facs="tcp:13754:41" rendition="simple:additions"/>
That wee may be perfect, wee muſt haue per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection two wayes,<note place="margin">Aquin. in Heb, cap. <hi>5.</hi> lect. <hi>2.</hi>
                  </note> ſaith <hi>Aquinas:</hi> Firſt, <hi>ſecun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dùm intellectum,</hi> in our <hi>underſtanding,</hi> by being able to diſcerne and judge aright of things: ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, <hi>ſecundùm affectum,</hi> in our <hi>affection,</hi> by charitie, cleaving wholy to God. For charitie is in a ſort of as large extent as inherent righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe, being the fulfilling of the Law, the mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of obedience and every good worke.</p>
               <p>We are perfect in that wee haue faith, hope, and other vertues truely in ſome meaſure: but in that we haue them not in full meaſure, we are im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfect. and ſo our perfection, though true, is ſtill imperfect. St. <hi>Paul</hi> ſaid of himſelfe he was not perfected, <hi>Phil.</hi> 3.12. after in the fifteenth verſe he calles himſelfe perfect:<note place="margin">Fulg. de prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſtin. ad Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nimum. li. <hi>10.</hi>
                  </note> Whereupon <hi>Fulgen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tius</hi> ſaith of him; <hi>He was perfect by expectation of reward, imperfect through weariſomeneſſe of the combat; Hee was perfect, in that with his minde he ſerved the Law of God, he was imperfect, in that with his fleſh he ſerved the Law of ſinne.</hi> Thus it was in the choſen veſſell of mercy; much more in us in whom all our <hi>perfection</hi> is ever attended with many <hi>imperfections.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="31" type="chapter">
               <pb n="73" facs="tcp:13754:41" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XXXI.</hi> Of perfect righteouſneſſe in this life more punctually and plainly.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>S all the lines in a Circle paſſing from the Circumference through the mediate meete in the Center; So all the righteous workes of the Saints proceeding from grace through faith are terminated and mee<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e in the Center of Gods glorie;<note place="margin">1 Cor. 10.31.</note> according to that pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept of the Apoſtle, <hi>Doe all to theglorie of God:</hi> and ſurely to doe ſo is true perfection.</p>
               <p>Now every thing is perfect, ſaith <hi>Aquinas,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Aquin. in Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lip. cap. <hi>3.</hi> lect. <hi>2.</hi>
                  </note> in ſuch ſort, as it doth adhere to the perfection thereof; but our ultimate perfection is God and his glory; now to referre all our actions totally and actually to God and his glorie, is <hi>perfectio patriae, the perfection of our heavenly Countrie,</hi> and not to be found in any man on earth, ſaue in <hi>Chriſt</hi> onely, who in the dayes of his fleſh was both <hi>Viator</hi> and <hi>Comprehenſor,</hi> both in the ſtate of grace and ſtate of glory. But,<note place="margin">Aquin. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> ſupra.</note> as <hi>Aquinas</hi> ſaith againe, <hi>to apply our hearts in nothing unto that which is againſt God,</hi> and referre our whole life habitually unto God, is <hi>perfectio viae, that per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection of us way-faring pilgrims,<note place="margin">☞</note> ad quam omnes tenentur ex neceſſitate ſalutis; whereunto all are bound upon neceſſitie of ſalvation.</hi> No man doth
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:13754:42" rendition="simple:additions"/>actually referre his whole life unto God and his glorie;<note place="margin">Eccleſ. 7.20. James 3.2.</note> for <hi>there is noman juſt an earth, which doth good and ſinneth not: and in many things wee all offend. David</hi> and St. <hi>Peter,</hi> and other holy men of God had their faults and errors, and yet were habitually righteous; therefore remarkeable is that excellent obſervation of St. <hi>Ambroſe, Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vina juſticia Denitune juſti,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">☞ Ambr. in Luc. cap. <hi>1.</hi>
                  </note> ex <hi>mantir habitu, non aliquo factor <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> God <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> meaſare the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> of the righteous, by <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> minde, not by ſome event of workes.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> none could be righteous, none would <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> none could expect the reward of glory: it is the triumphant Church, which is all faire, and <hi>there is no <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="5 letters">
                        <desc>•••••</desc>
                     </gap>iſh in hen.</hi> There fore howſoever the perfectiſts con<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>iue of it, it is moſt true which St. <hi>Auguſtine</hi> writeth;<note place="margin">Aug. de eccl. dogm. cap. <hi>85.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Nullus ſanctus &amp; juſtus caret peceato, thee tamen hoc deſinit eſſe ſanctus &amp; juſtus, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap>: no juſt and holy man is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> ſildae; never the leſſe he doth nick ceaſe to be holy and juſt, ſeting in affection he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taines ſanctitis.</hi> So that ſtill a man may be habi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tually <hi>righteous,</hi> who is not without all error and actuall prevarication.</p>
               <p>To loue and affect holineſſe is a degree of ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſſe; as to deſire and endeavour to be perfect is a degree of perfection according to that in St. <hi>Bernard,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Bern. ad Ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rin. Abb. ep. <hi>254.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Studere perfectioni perfectio eſt, to ſtudy to be perfect is perfection. Luther</hi> writes of one <hi>Staupitius,</hi> a godly learned man, that <hi>he vowed a thouſand times,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Luther in Gal. cap. <hi>5.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>that he would become a better man; yet after all his vowes he perceived no impreouement
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:13754:42" rendition="simple:additions"/>or bettering of himſelfe.</hi> Now in that he was not better, he was imperfect, but in as much as be deſired carneſtly, and endeavoured to be a bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter man, he was perfect.<note place="margin">Bern. uhi ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pro.</note> For as Saint <hi>Bernard</hi> ſaith, <hi>Indefeſſum proficiendi ſtudium &amp; jugis cona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus ad perfectionens perfectio reputatur: An inde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fatigable deſire of profiting and continwall endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vouring to be perfect is perfection.</hi> Wee deſire to be vertuous holy and good, but are not ſuch as we deſire to be, and therefore St. <hi>Auguſtine</hi> ſaith,<note place="margin">Aug. <hi>1.</hi> cp. Ioan. ca. <hi>3.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Tota vita boni Chriſtiani ſanctum deſiderium est, the whole life of a Chriſtian is an holy deſire;</hi> but if there be in us a deſire, a readie and willing mind, God will accept of that from us, which he him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe hath wrought in us. If through <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> of <hi>Christ</hi> ſanctifying of us and renew<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> Gods image, we bring <hi>forth the fruits of the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Rom. 7.6.</note> 
                  <hi>walking in newneſſe of Spirit, and not in the oldneſſe of the Letter, then are we perfect according to the ſtate of this life.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>If we <hi>walke in the Spirit,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Gal. 5.16.</note> ſtriving againſt ſinne and the fleſh, wraſtling with Satan and the world, obeying the ſecret motions and ſweet invitations of grace; then are wee perfect,<note place="margin">Aug. de doct. Chriſt. <hi>3.39.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>quanturn in hac vita,</hi> as St. <hi>Auguſtine</hi> ſpeakes, with ſuch a mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of perfection as is attaineable in this life.</p>
               <p>If ſo be then we referre our whole life to God and his glorie, if wee endeavour and ſtudie to walke in the Spirit, and to bring forth abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dantly the fruits of the Spirit, then are wee per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect, for wee keepe the Law, ſeeing the righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe of the Law is fulfilled in them,<note place="margin">Rom. 8.3.</note> 
                  <hi>who walke
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:13754:43" rendition="simple:additions"/>not after the fleſh, but after the Spirit.</hi> And if wee doe this, what is it but to doe the will of God, but to pleaſe God, but to hearken unto the voice of God ſpeaking to <hi>Abraham</hi> the. Father of the faithfull, and in him to all that be of the faith of <hi>Abraham,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Ger. 17.1.</note> ſaying; <hi>I am the almightie God, walke thou before me and be thou prefect.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="32" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XXXII.</hi> Of Perſeverance.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">P</seg>Erſeverance is a ſtable and firme conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuance in grace and righteouſneſſe. And it is a ſingular gift of God not to be acquired by humane meanes or merits. It is a rare and admirable vertue, which the old Philoſophers and Sages of the world could not well underſtand; and no marvaile, ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>Adam</hi> adorned with ſuch ornaments of grace did not learne it in Paradiſe. Now this ſingular gift and rare endowment is neceſſarily required to the conſummating of our perfection by inhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent righteouſneſſe. This the firſt <hi>Adam</hi> wanted, this the ſecond <hi>Adam</hi> in whom is the fulneſſe of all grace, freely conferreth and beſtoweth on us; and therefore <hi>Fulgentius</hi> ſaith well, <hi>Per illum a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſimus priorem gratiam, periſtum recepimus am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliorem;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Fulg. ferm. de dup. nat.</note> 
                  <hi>By him</hi> (the firſt <hi>Adam</hi>) <hi>wee loſt the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer grace: by this</hi> (the ſecond <hi>Adam</hi>) <hi>we haue re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived more ample grace.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="77" facs="tcp:13754:43" rendition="simple:additions"/>
Although <hi>Adam</hi> was perfect and righteous in the day he was created, yet for want of perſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance hee became imperfect and unrighteous: whereupon St. <hi>Auguſtine</hi> noteth thus much; <hi>Et<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſi peceatum in ſolo libero arbitrio erat conſtitutum;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Aug. Ench. ad Laur. cap. <hi>106.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> temen retinen dae juſtitiaeſufficie<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>at ſolum libe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ru<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> arbitrium, niſi participatione immu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>abilis boni divinam adintorium praberetur; Although ſinne ſtood in the free will alone; yet the free will alone was not ſufficient to retaine righteouſneſſe, unleſſe divine ayde was aff<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>ded by partaking of the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>changeable good.</hi> So that as without perſeverance we cannot hold on our way and retaine righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe; ſo neither without it can wee be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected and conſummate in righteouſneſſe.</p>
               <p>Hell is full of good purpoſes, but no perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mances of good be there: therefore now let us not be wearie of well-doing, for in due ſeaſon we ſhall reape an eternall reward. Let us not be like to pope <hi>Eugenius,</hi> to whom St. <hi>Bernard</hi> ſaith,<note place="margin">Bern. de con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſid. ad Eug. li. cap. <hi>1.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Vbi incipis, ibi deſicis, where thou beginneſt, there thou endest.</hi> When we purpoſe to aſcend up into the tabernacle of the Lord, and climbe up the craggie rocke of vertue, wee muſt not delay and conferre with fleſh and bloud, or ſtand to parley with the world, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>it is no fit time to ſit downe and demurre;</hi> for as St. <hi>Ambroſe</hi> ſaith, <hi>Dum cunctaris &amp; dubitas, iter quod ingreſſus es per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>didiſti, whilſt thou delayeſt and doubteſt,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Ambr. in ſeſt. Cathedrae S<hi rend="sup">d</hi> Petri.</note> 
                  <hi>thou haſt loſt thy journey, which thou didſt begin.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The traveller by holding on his way with pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience, at length commeth to his inne; the little
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:13754:44" rendition="simple:additions"/>bird carrying at hee bill a little clay or ſtraw, and ſuch like matter, by little and little at length ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſheth her neſt; the Merchant patiently holding on his courſe amids many ſtornes and tempeſts, and other dangers at Sea, at length commeth to the Haven where he would be; the painefull Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon by laying ſtone upon ſtone, in continding his labour, at length erects a ſtately and goodly buil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding. Now if diligent <hi>perſeverance</hi> be able to doe theſe things, being aſſiſted by nature, how much more powerfull ſhall he be in ſpirituall af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faires, being aſſiſted by grace. Oh let us be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant, immoveable, alwayes abounding in the workes of righteouſneſſe; let us not faint nor fayle in doing well, that we may obtaine an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heritance which faileth not: let us by patient continuance in well doing, ſeeke for honour and glorie and immortalitie,<note place="margin">Rom. 2.7.</note> then ſhall God <hi>render unto us eternall life. Chriſt is the forerunner,</hi> Heb. 6.20. we muſt with the Apoſtle, <hi>Philip.</hi> 3. <hi>ver.</hi> 12. <hi>follow after,</hi> and that with all diligence and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant perſeverance;<note place="margin">Bern. ep. <hi>254.</hi>
                  </note> for as St. <hi>Bernard</hi> ſaith, <hi>Quid prodeſt Chriſtum ſequi, ſi non contingat renſequi? What will it avaite us to follow after Chriſt, if hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pily we overtake him not?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Though thou run never ſo, if thou continueſt not unto death, ſaith he, <hi>Bravium non apprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dis, Bravium Chriſtus eſt: thou layeſt not hold on the prize, the prize is Chriſt.</hi> Wherefore if hee running on, thou makeſt a ſtand, thou commeſt not nearer unto him, but ſetreſt thy ſelfe further off from him. Surely the faithfull and zealous
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:13754:44" rendition="simple:additions"/>follower will runne and not be wearie; the righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous will <hi>hold on his way,</hi> ſaith <hi>Iob,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Iob 17.9.</note> and <hi>he that hath cleane hands</hi> ſhall be ſtronger and ſtronger. But <hi>you haue neede of patience,</hi> ſaith the Apoſtle, that <hi>after you haue done the will of God, you might receiue the promiſe: Vt perſeveret is in agonè,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Amb. in Heb. cap. <hi>10.</hi> v. <hi>36.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>do. nec recipiatis coronam condignam labori veſtro,</hi> ſaith S. <hi>Ambroſe, you haue neede of patience, that yee may perſevere in the combat, untill yee receine a crowne meete for your labour.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Perſeverance immediately beginneth to attend on grace, the mother of all vertues, when it is firſt infuſed, but is not compleate untill death, untill the infuſion of finall grace, which per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectly extinguiſheth all evill concupiſcence, and is the utter deletion or taking away of all ſinne and ſinfulneſſe.</p>
               <p>As the Crowne on the Kings head giveth an eminent ſplend our and luſter to his royall robes, and other <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> ornaments: ſo the grace of per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeverance is the glorious complement &amp; crowne of all other vertues, and is an infallible guide to leade us into the kingdome of glorie. Therefore our Saviour ſaith not, <hi>he that ſhall begin,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Math. 24.13.</note> 
                  <hi>but he that ſhall endure unto the end ſhall be ſaved.</hi> And to the Angell in the Church of <hi>Smyrna,</hi> he ſaith, <hi>Be thou faithfull unto death, and I will giue thee a crowne of life.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Apoc. 2.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>0.</note>
               </p>
               <p>We are now in our ſpirituall courſe and race, we muſt ſo runne, that we may obtaine, wee are now in the combat, we muſt ſo fight that we may over come. Which that we may doe, we are to
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:13754:45" rendition="simple:additions"/>implore and deſire by fervent and inceſſant pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, that God would prevent and follow us with grace all the dayes of our life; that ſo at the end of our dayes, we may confidently and comforta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly ſay with the choſen veſſell of mercy, <hi>I have fought a good fight,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">2 Tim. 4. v. 7, 8.</note> 
                  <hi>I haue finiſhed my courſe, I haue kept the faith. Henceforth there is laid up for me a crowne of righteouſneſſe, which the Lord the righteous Iudge ſhall giue me at that day: and not unto me onely, but unto them alſo which loue his appearing.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="33" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XXXIII.</hi> Of perfection in glorie.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>Aint <hi>Paul</hi> the choſen veſſell of mercy and trumpet of grace,<note place="margin">Rom. 8.30.</note> uniteth and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth up the golden chaine of our ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation with foure linkes. Firſt, <hi>Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſtination:</hi> ſecondly, <hi>Vocation:</hi> thirdly, <hi>Iuſtifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation:</hi> fourthly, <hi>Glorification.</hi> Where hee ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſeth not our ſanctification, as being included in our glorification; according to the expoſition of <hi>Aquinas,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Aquin. in cp. ad Rom. cap. <hi>8.</hi>
                  </note> ſaying, <hi>Glorificamur in hac vita per prefectune virturis &amp; gratia: in futura per exalta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionem gloria: We are glorified in this life by profi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciency of vertue and grace: in the life to come, by exaltation of glory.</hi> And indeed grace is glorie in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>choate or begun; glorie is grace conſummate and perfected: and our imperfect perfection by grace
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:13754:45" rendition="simple:additions"/>here is a previous preparing and diſpoſing of us unto that abſolute perfection which wee ſhall haue, being cloathed and adorned with the ſtole of glorie. For even in this life wee are freed in part from thoſe foure evills which are maine im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pediments to our abſolute perfection: and this freedome is meerely from grace in <hi>Chriſt Ieſus.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The firſt evill hindering our perfection, is <hi>er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror in the underſtanding,</hi> from which we are freed in part by the <hi>Spirit of grace,</hi> leading of us into all truth, and teaching us all things neceſſary unto ſalvation.</p>
               <p>The ſecond evill, a let to perfection, is <hi>ſinne in the will,</hi> from which wee are alſo partly freed by grace in <hi>Chriſt,</hi> and that two wayes; Firſt,<note place="margin">Rom. 6.14.</note> from the dominion of it, <hi>For ſinne ſhall not haue domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion over you, becauſe yee are not under the Law, but under grace,</hi> ſaith the Apoſtle; ſecondly, from the condemnation of ſinne, ſeeing,<note place="margin">Rom. 8.1.</note> 
                  <hi>there is no condemnation to them, which are in Chriſt Ieſus, which walke not after the fleſh, but after the Spirit.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The third evill hindrance of our perfection, is <hi>miſery and afflictions,</hi> from which by faith and ſpirituall <hi>fortitude</hi> we are freed in part, that they may not ſwallow us up, that the flouds of great waters, the over-flowings of feare and deſpaire may never prevaile againſt us, never over whelme us. <hi>In the world you ſhall haue tribulation; but be of good cheare,</hi> ſaith <hi>Chriſt, I haue overcome the world.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The laſt evill letting our perfection, is <hi>death.</hi> And from this alſo we are freed in part by grace,
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:13754:46" rendition="simple:additions"/>not onely from ſpirituall and eternall death, but even from corporall in two reſpects: Firſt, from the <hi>ſting</hi> thereof,<note place="margin">1 Iohn 1. v. 7.</note> which is ſinne, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.56. for <hi>by the bloud of Chriſt wee are cleanſed from all ſinne.</hi> Secondly, in <hi>regard of dominion,</hi> for death ſhall not tyrannize over us for ever; for in the <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection at the ſound of the Trumpet,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1 Cor. 15.52.</note> 
                  <hi>wee ſhall be raiſed incorruptible,</hi> and never die any more. Whereas the bodies of the unjuſt ſhall riſe, but from corporall to <hi>eternall death,</hi> wherein they ſhall be ever dying, but never dead, which mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved holy <hi>Bernard</hi> to cry out,<note place="margin">Bern. de con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſid. li. <hi>5.</hi> ca. <hi>12.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Alas,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>quis det illis ſemel mori, ut non moriantur in aternum? who might grant them once to die, that ſo they might not die for ever?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Thus are we freed in part by grace from theſe foure evill impediments of perfection. But in the ſtare of glorie, we ſhall be wholy and entirely exempted from the in for then ſhall we be free from all darkneſſe of error, obliquitie of ſinne, from all of ſtictive miſery and deſtroying death. Yea, we ſhall be free from them after a more ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent mother, than <hi>Adam</hi> was in Paradiſe in the ſtate of innocency. For it pleaſed the omni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>potent goodneſſe and wiſedome (who bringeth light out of darkneſſe, life out of death, and good out of evill) even by the fall of man to raiſe him up in <hi>Chriſt</hi> to a more eminent and high ſtate of perfection.</p>
               <p>It is true that <hi>Adam</hi> in his integritie had power not to erre, not to ſinne, not to ſuffer miſery, not to die: but it is alſo true that he had power
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:13754:46" rendition="simple:additions"/>to erre, to ſinne, to ſuffer miſery, to die, which by wofull experiment he brought into act, by diſobeying the command of his creator. Ever ſince the poiſon and contagion of diſobedience hath tainted and corrupted all the veines of his rebellious children and miſerable poſteritie.</p>
               <p>Now in the ſtate of glory in that heavenly Paradiſe, we ſhall obtaine ſuch a tranſcendent degree of perfection, as that we ſhall haue no power in our underſtanding to erre, in our will to ſinne, no power to ſuffer miſery and devou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring death.</p>
               <p>In that ineffable glorie wee being perfectly changed into the image of the Lord, the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of all things ſhall be ſeene of us, not by <hi>parts, but wholly and at once,</hi> as St. <hi>Proſper</hi> ſaith.<note place="margin">Proſp. de vita contemplat. li. <hi>1.</hi> cap. <hi>6.</hi>
                  </note> We ſhall ſee all things clearely without error, by beholding him who is all truth: Now wee ſee through a glaſſe darkly that incomprehenſible light; we behold him now through a three-fold glaſſe; Firſt, of the creatures, ſecondly, of his workes of juſtice and mercie, thirdly, of the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Scriptures: But then we ſhall ſee him perfect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, clearely, face to face, with unſpeakeable joy and delight: and herein confiſts our eſſentiall, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſufficient bleſſedneſſe, therefore <hi>Philip</hi> ſaid unto <hi>Chriſt, Lord ſhew us the Father and it ſufficeth.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Iohn 14.8.</note>
               </p>
               <p>Now we know God but imperfectly, enigma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tically; but then we ſhall know him, with a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect, cleare Meridian knowledge; we ſhall know him as we are knowne of him, and as he is known of the Angels in Heaven.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="84" facs="tcp:13754:47" rendition="simple:additions"/>
The man which was called by the Lord Ieſus in a Viſion, the man which was taken up into the third heaven, and ſaw things not to be uttered, hath revealed this unto us in thoſe words,<note place="margin">1 Cor. 13.12.</note> 
                  <hi>Now we ſee through a glaſſe darkly, but then face to face: now I know in part, but then ſhall I know, even as I and knowne.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Aquin. in</hi> 2 Cor. 3.18.</note> What is knowledge, but <hi>aſſimilatio cognoſeentis ad cognitum, a making of the ſubject knowing, like to the object which is knowne.</hi> So by knowing God perfectly, we are made perfectly like unto him: and being made perfectly like un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to him, we know him perfectly. So the Virgin-Apoſtle and Prophet of the New Teſtament di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinely argueth, ſaying, but <hi>wee know, that when He ſhall appeare,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1 Iohn 3.2.</note> 
                  <hi>wee ſhall be like him: for wee ſhall ſee him as he is.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>As touching perfection in the will, the eſtate of the Saints in heaven ſhall farre excell that of <hi>Adam</hi> in Paradiſe; for he in his innocency there, as St. <hi>Bernard</hi> notes,<note place="margin">Bern. de gra. &amp; lib. arb.</note> had but an <hi>inferiour free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, Poſſe non peceare, a power not to ſinne;</hi> whereas the glorified ones in heaven ſhall haue a ſuperiour freedome, <hi>Non poſſe peccare no power to ſinne.</hi> For they ſhall alwayes behold God, the chiefe good, the fountaine of good, who maketh all them bleſſed, who ſo behold him: and that bleſſednes is ſuch as includes all ſufficient good, and excludes all deficient evill from them that haue it. Seeing they are now free Denizens and glorious Citizens of that holy <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi> where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of St. <hi>Gregorie</hi> ſaith,<note place="margin">Greg. in ſept. Pſal. paen. in fine.</note> 
                  <hi>In eam nullus ingreditur im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pius, nullus habitat iniquus, nullus intrat immun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dus,
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:13754:47" rendition="simple:additions"/>None that is ungodly goeth into it, none that is unjuſt dwelleth in it, none that is uncleane entreth into it.</hi> There is no impietie, no iniquirie, no im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puritie: no evills, no ſinnes approach thither; for as St. <hi>Proſper</hi> ſaith, <hi>Nec peccata ibi ulla,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Proſp. de vita contempl. li. <hi>1.</hi> cap. <hi>4.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>nec peccatores erunt, &amp; qui ibi fuerint, jam peccare non poterint, There ſhall neither be any ſinnes, nor ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, and they that ſhall be there, ſhall now haue no power to ſinne.</hi> For they can will nothing but that which is good, ſeeing they be now neceſſarily good, not by any iron neceſſitie of compulſion or coaction, for there is no ſuch thing there; but by a golden neceſſitie of immutabilitie, which ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver altereth, never changeth. Such ſhall be the ineffable felicitie of the glorified Saints in hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, being now bleſſed with Angelicall perfecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, being made like unto the Angels in heaven.</p>
               <p>God is righteous, and therefore bleſſed, wee are now unrighteous, and therefore miſerable: but then being conformed to the image of God, we ſhall be righteous, and therefore bleſſed, and conſequently free from all miſerie, both in ſoule and bodie. For whereas <hi>Adam</hi> had in this alſo,<note place="margin">Bern. de Gra. &amp; lib. Arb.</note> an inferiour freedome, <hi>Poſſe non turbari, a power not to be troubled; We ſhall then haue,</hi> as St. <hi>Ber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nard</hi> noteth, <hi>a ſuperiour freedome,</hi> a <hi>non poſſe tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bari, no power to be troubled,</hi> to ſuffer any afflictiue miſery whatſoever. Our ſoules ſhall be free from any diſtemper, paſſion, and perturbation.<note place="margin">Aquin. in <hi>1 Cor.</hi> cap. <hi>15.</hi> lect. <hi>6.</hi>
                  </note> Our bodies ſhall be qualified with foure endowments like to the <hi>Sunne.</hi> Firſt, <hi>claritie,</hi> ſecondly, <hi>agili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie,</hi> thirdly, <hi>ſubtilitie,</hi> fourthly, <hi>impaſſibilitie.</hi>
                  <pb n="86" facs="tcp:13754:48" rendition="simple:additions"/>But what did I ſay, like to the <hi>Sunne?</hi> nay, rather like to the ſonne of God, for we ſhall be like him in <hi>corporis gloria,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Ambr. in ca. <hi>6.</hi> ad Roman.</note> 
                  <hi>non in divinitatis natura, in the glory of his bodie, not in the nature of his divinitie,</hi> ſaith St. <hi>Ambroſe.</hi> For in the reſurrection He will change us in a moment: then as the Apoſtle teacheth us,<note place="margin">Phil. 3.21.</note> 
                  <hi>He ſhall change our vile body, that it may be faſhioned like to his glorious body.</hi> So that we ſhall be free from all miſery, as he is free in his bodie. Our ſenſes and other faculties ſhall not be ſubject to any offence or hurt. Our bodies ſhall no more be expoſed to wounds, maimes, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects, no diſtemper or paine, no diſeaſe or infir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitie ſhall annoy them. All tarditie and ſlownes of the mooving facultie ſhall be taken away, for the bodie being now ſpirituall, ſhall goe without any delay,<note place="margin">Proſp. de vita contemp. lib. <hi>1.</hi> cap. <hi>11.</hi>
                  </note> hindrance, or difficultie, <hi>Quecun<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> ire voluerit Spiritus angelicae beatitudinis aqualitate perfectus, whither ſoever the Spirit will goe, being perfect in equalitie, with Angelicall bleſſedneſſe,</hi> as St. <hi>Proſper</hi> ſaith.</p>
               <p>Thus where the cauſe is taken away, the effect muſt needs ceaſe: the evill of puniſhment ſhall al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes be abſent, where the evill of ſinne is never preſent. For how is it poſſible that any miſerie ſhould be there, where there is perfect charitie without diſſimulation or hatred, perfect peace without diſſenſion or diſcord, perfect health without languor or infirmitie: where there is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but eternall happineſſe and everlaſting feli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citie.</p>
               <p>And the reaſon of all this is given by St. <hi>Iohn,</hi>
                  <pb n="87" facs="tcp:13754:48" rendition="simple:additions"/>ſaying, <hi>for the Lambe,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Revel. 7.17.</note> 
                  <hi>which is in the midſt of the throne, ſhall feede them, and leade them unto living fountaines of waters: and God ſhall wipe away all teares from their eyes.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="34" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XXXIIII.</hi> Of perfection by immortalitie in glorie.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He firſt act of our eſſence is life, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out which, wee haue no motion or ſenſe, no underſtanding, willing, or working. Hereupon bleſſedneſſe, which conſiſteth in act, is properly aſcribed to life, and to that life which is eternall and immor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall. Many of the old Philoſophers held immor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>talitie of the ſoule, but not of the bodie, that was an idle fancie, groſſe, and abſurd with them. But we know by the Chriſtian veritie, and ſtead<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faſtly beleeue, that <hi>our bodies in the reſurrection ſhall riſe incorruptible, and liue ever.</hi> For although the bodies of reprobates ſhall me againe and liue ever, <hi>Quead ſubſtantiam vivendi, in reſpect of the ſubſtance of life,</hi> yet <hi>quoad qualitatem vivendi, in regard of the qualitie of life,</hi> they being in perpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall horror and torments, are rightly ſaid to pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh and die eternally.<note place="margin">Aug. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> cap. <hi>92.</hi>
                  </note> Seeing as St. <hi>Auguſtine</hi> ſaith, <hi>Vera vita non eſt, niſi ubi faliciter vivitur, It is not true life, but where there is an happie life.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Neither may it ſeeme ſtrange that a body glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rified ſhould be immortall, ſeeing the body of
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:13754:49" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <hi>Adam</hi> in the ſtate of innocency in that earthly Paradiſe was immortall. For as St. <hi>Auguſtine</hi> affirmeth, that the body of <hi>Adam</hi> before ſinne, was both mortall and immortall;<note place="margin">Aug. in Gen. ad lit. lib. <hi>6.</hi> cap. <hi>25.</hi>
                  </note> mortall, <hi>quia poterat mori, becauſe it had a power to die,</hi> and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortall, <hi>quia poter at non mori, becauſe it had a pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er not to die.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Adam</hi> no doubt had <hi>temperamentum abſolutè temperatiſſimum, a temperament abſolutely moſt temperate,</hi> ſuch as none but he and the <hi>Second A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam</hi> are ſuppoſed to haue: yet that was not ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient to immortalitie. And therefore by Gods gracious indulgence he might freely feede on the tree of life; by meanes whereof he might be pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved from decaying by age or any other cauſe, and that through ſome naturall vertue in the tree, or rather Gods bleſſing, or both. And thus <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam</hi> was mortall,<note place="margin">Aug. ubi ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prd.</note> 
                  <hi>conditione corporis animalis, by the condition of a naturall body,</hi> but immortall, <hi>beneficie conditoris, by the benefit of his creator,</hi> as St. <hi>Auguſtine</hi> excellently explaineth it. If ſo be that <hi>Adam</hi> had not ſinned, yet <hi>fuiſſet mortalis, he ſhould haue beene mortall;</hi> nevertheleſſe, if he had not ſinned,<note place="margin">Valleſ. ſacra. Philoſ. c. <hi>6.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>fuiſſet nunquam moriturus, he ſhould ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver haue died,</hi> as <hi>Valleſius</hi> aptly noteth. So then no ſinne,<note place="margin">Rom. 5.12.</note> no death; <hi>By one man ſinne entred into the world, and death by ſinne.</hi> Contrary to the hereſie of <hi>Pelagius</hi> and <hi>Augustinus Steuchus,</hi> a Pontifician of later times.<note place="margin">Whitak. de not. eccl. ca. <hi>7.</hi>
                  </note>
               </p>
               <p>If <hi>Adam</hi> then had not ſinned, he had not died, but ſhould haue beene immortall, <hi>Immortalitate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minori, in qua poſſet mori,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Aug. Ench. cap. <hi>105.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>with a leſſer immortali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie,
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:13754:49" rendition="simple:additions"/>wherein he had a power to die,</hi> ſaith S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
                  <hi>Auguſtine-Quamvis major futura ſit, in qua non poſſit mori, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though a greater immortalitie be to come, wherein he cannot die.</hi> And this muſt be in Heaven, in the ſtate of glory, where is no diſobedience or ſinne, and conſequently, <hi>no death;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Rom. 6.23.</note> for as the Apoſtle ſaith, <hi>the wages of ſinne is death.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Chriſt Ieſus is our life,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Col. 3.4.</note> both here in the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of grace, and there in the kingdome of glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie. For He as head and fountaine of life, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municateth life to all the members of his myſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call body; He being the laſt <hi>Adam,</hi> who was made a <hi>quickening Spirit,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1 Cor. 15.45.</note> enlivening us not onely with <hi>naturall, ſenſitiue,</hi> and <hi>rationall life,</hi> as our <hi>Creator,</hi> but alſo with <hi>ſpirituall life,</hi> as our <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deemer,</hi> and <hi>eternall life,</hi> as our <hi>Glorifier.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Auguſtus</hi> the Emperour <hi>in Romani nominis ae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternitatem natus, borne to eternize the Roman name,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Onuph. de im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perat. Com. cap. <hi>4.</hi>
                  </note> according to <hi>Onnphrius,</hi> was wont many times as <hi>Suetonius</hi> writes in his life, to pray for <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>,<note place="margin">Sueton. in vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ta Auguſti. cap. <hi>99.</hi>
                  </note> for his friends and himſelfe, not <hi>immortalitie,</hi> but <hi>aneaſie death without paine.</hi> But our bleſſed Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our did not onely pray for, but doth alſo giue un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to his friends, his my ſticall members, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>immortalitie:</hi> for ſpeaking of them, his <hi>Sheepe,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Iohn. 10.28.</note> he ſaith, <hi>I giue unto them eternall life, and they ſhall never periſh, neither ſhall any man plucke them out of my hands.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Our life conſiſts in the knowledge and loue of Chriſt,</hi> ſaith <hi>Aquinas: we know Him,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Aquin. in <hi>Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſt.</hi> cap. <hi>3.</hi> lect. <hi>1.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>and loue Him in this world in part, and it is our ſpirituall life; we ſhall know him and loue him in the other world per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectly,
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:13754:50" rendition="simple:additions"/>and that will be eternall life.</hi> As the firſt <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam</hi> brought death into the world, ſo the ſecond <hi>Adam</hi> aboliſhing <hi>death,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">2 Tim. 1.10.</note> 
                  <hi>hath brought life and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortalitie to light.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Aug. in Ioan. tract. <hi>22.</hi>
                  </note> Who according to St. <hi>Augu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtine,</hi> ſpeaketh on this wiſe to <hi>thee, Wouldst thou not erre? I am the way. Wouldſt thou not be decei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved? I am the truth. Wouldſt thou not die? I am the life.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Iohn 14.6.</note> 
                  <hi>I am the way, the truth, and the life.</hi> So may I ſay unto thee, Wouldſt thou not haue thy body perpetually detained under the power of dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and dominion of the graue:<note place="margin">Iohn 11.25.</note> 
                  <hi>Loe,</hi> He ſaith, <hi>I am the reſurrection and the life.</hi> Beleeue on me, let me be thy ſpirituall foode, feede on me by faith; for <hi>He that eateth my fleſh, and drinketh my bloud, bath eternall life, and I will raiſe him up at the laſt day.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>If <hi>Chriſt dwell in us</hi> now by faith ſpiritually,<note place="margin">Ephel. 3.17.</note> he will ſurely <hi>dwell</hi> in us hereafter by glory e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternally: and that after an admirable manner, which now we know not;<note place="margin">1 Iohn 3.2.</note> For now we <hi>are ſonnes of God,</hi> ſaith St. <hi>Iohn, but it doth not yet appeare what we ſhall be.</hi> It is not here revealed unto us, we are unworthy to know it, we are unable to comprehend it. Onely thus much we are taught out of the divine Oracles, that in the ſtole of glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, we ſhall ſee God clearely, face to face, wee ſhall with unſpeakeable joy and delight ever be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold Him, who is the <hi>bleſſed life</hi> of man, ſaith St. <hi>Auguſtine;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Aug de civit. Dei. lib. <hi>19.</hi> cap. <hi>26.</hi>
                  </note> whom to behold <hi>is life,</hi> and the life <hi>is eternall.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="35" type="chapter">
               <pb n="91" facs="tcp:13754:50" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XXXV.</hi> Of different perfection in glorie.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>Pirituall gifts and graces are diverſly diſpenſed by <hi>Chriſt,</hi> and given to the Saints on earth after a different man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner: <hi>For to every one is given grace according to the meaſure of the gift of Chriſt.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Epheſ. 4.7.</note> Thus much the Apoſtle inſtancing in ſome particular graces, inſinuateth touching faith, the prime car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinall vertue, he ſaith,<note place="margin">Rom. 12.3, 6.</note> God <hi>dealeth to every man the meaſure of faith:</hi> and <hi>a proportion of faith:</hi> and entreating of chaſtitie and continency, he ſaid, <hi>Every man hath his proper gift of God,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1 Cor. 7.7.</note> 
                  <hi>one after this manner and another after that.</hi> When as the Apoſtles ſaid to our Saviour, if the caſe was ſuch, it was not good to marry; <hi>He anſwered them, all men cannot receiue this ſaying,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Math. 19.11. <hi>Ambr. de voc. gent. li.</hi> 2. <hi>c.</hi> 3.</note> 
                  <hi>ſaue they to whom it is given.</hi> Hereupon St. <hi>Ambroſe</hi> ſaith, <hi>Multis modis &amp; innumer abilibus differentijs, gratia opera &amp; dona variantur; in<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> ipſis ſingulis generibus mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neruns diſſimiles ſunt gradus &amp; impares quantita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes: The gifts and workes of grace are varied after many manners and innumerable differences: and in the ſeverall kindes of gifts, there be unlike de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees and unequall quantities.</hi> Now as there are many different degrees of grace in the militant Church: ſo there be alſo many different degrees of glorie in the triumphant Church,<note place="margin">Ambr. de bon. mort. cap. <hi>11.</hi>
                  </note> according to that of St. <hi>Ambroſe, Erit or do diverſus clarita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:13754:51" rendition="simple:additions"/>&amp; gloria, ſicut erit meritorum: There ſhall be a different order of excellency and glory, as there ſhall be of merits.</hi> Hence it was that St. <hi>Auguſtine</hi> upon thoſe words of <hi>Chriſt,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Aug. in Ioan. cap. <hi>14.</hi> v. <hi>2.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>in my Fathers houſe are many manſions,</hi> ſaith, they are <hi>diverſae meritorum in una vita aterna dignitates; diverſe dignities of merits in one eternall life.</hi> And St. <hi>Hierome</hi> ſaith, <hi>Multae ſunt manſiones apud patrem,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Hieren. ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſ. Pelag. li. <hi>1.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>quia &amp; merita diverſa; there are many manſions with the Father, becauſe there are diverſe merits.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Here note by the way that St. <hi>Ambroſe,</hi> St. <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſtine,</hi> St. <hi>Hierome,</hi> and other of the ancient Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, by <hi>merits</hi> ſo freque<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly mentioned by them, underſtand good workes done of faith, as we doe generally take them; So as <hi>Bucer</hi> profeſſed in the conference at <hi>Ratisbon,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Bucer. apud Caſſand. Cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fut. art. <hi>6.</hi>
                  </note> ſaying, <hi>If by to merit, the Fathers and others underſtand, to doe through faith of the grace of God good workes, to which God hath promiſed and will render a reward.</hi> To uſe the word in this ſenſe, wee will not condemne. Wherein we wholly agree with St. <hi>Bernard,</hi> who explaineth the matter thus:<note place="margin">Bern. de Gra. &amp; lib. Arb.</note> 
                  <hi>Thoſe which wee call our merits, if they be properly called, are certaine ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minaries of hope, incentiues to charitie, ſignes of ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret predeſtination, preſages of future felicitie, the way to the kingdome, not the cauſe of raigning there.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Now correſpondent to our good workes in this life ſhall our <hi>eternall reward</hi> be in the other life:<note place="margin">Math. 16.27.</note> For <hi>the Sonne of man ſhall come in the glory of his Father with his Angels: and then ſhall he reward every man according to his workes.</hi> This our bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:13754:51" rendition="simple:additions"/>Saviour, <hi>the truth,</hi> hath taught us; and after him his choſen veſſell of mercy and trumpet of grace, hath delivered unto us the ſame infallible <hi>veritie,</hi> namely,<note place="margin">Rom. 2.6.</note> that <hi>God will render to every man according to his deeds.</hi> So that ſuch as our meaſure of grace is in this life, ſuch ſhall our meaſure of glory be in the other world: ſuch as our vertues and good workes be here, ſuch ſhall our happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and felicitie be there. Let us then, not be weary of well doing, knowing that in due ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon we ſhall reape, if we faint not. All that ſhall be judged worthy in <hi>Chriſt</hi> to enter into the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly Paradiſe, ſhall haue <hi>perfection of all parts</hi> and <hi>eſſentialls of glory, aquè, non aequaliper, one as well as another, not equally in degree one with wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</hi> All who haue faithfully laboured in <hi>Chriſt,</hi> Vineyard, ſhall at the end of the day receiue their penie, <hi>aqualem mercedem, vita, non gla<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ia,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Ambr. in Lus. cap. <hi>15.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>an e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quall reward of life, not of glory,</hi> according to St. <hi>Ambroſe:</hi> for ſuppoſe, faith he, there is not grace, one reward, <hi>diverſum tan<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>n bra<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>iu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> violeri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> eſt, yet the prize of victory is diverſe.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>It is true that in reſpect of the object participa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, one is not more bleſſed than another; all be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holding one God the fountaine of life. But in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard of the diſpoſition of the ſubjects participa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, one ſhall be more happie than another, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe one ſhall ſee God more clearely than ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, one ſhall loue God more perfectly and ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dently than another, and that in ſo large and am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple latitude, as we are not now able to compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hend.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="94" facs="tcp:13754:52" rendition="simple:additions"/>
The Apoſtleteacheth us,<note place="margin">1 Cor. 15. ve. 41, 42.</note> that <hi>there is one glory of the Sonne, another of the Moone, and another of the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ines for one ſtarre differeth from another ſtarre in glory. So is the reſurrection of the dead.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>They that be wiſe ſhall ſhine as the brightneſſe of the fir<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="4 letters">
                        <desc>••••</desc>
                     </gap> at:<note place="margin">Dam. 12.3.</note> and they that turne many unto righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenaſneſſe, as the ſtarres for ever and ever.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Now although every ſtarre be perfect in it ſelfe, yet in compariſon of a greater it may want per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection,<note place="margin">Hieron. ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſ. Pelag. lib. <hi>1.</hi>
                  </note> as St. <hi>Hierome</hi> notes: So although every glorified Saint ſhall be perfect in it ſelfe, yet may ſuch compared to others more glorious want perfection, not of parts or eſſentialls, but of de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grere of glorie: But all ſhall be perfect, all accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to their proper meaſure and capacitie, ſhall b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>fully f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>led with glorie, none ſhall want, all <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> enough,<note place="margin">Proſp. de vita <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>. <hi>1.</hi> cap. <hi>4.</hi>
                  </note> all ſhall haue ſufficient, <hi>Quia ſingulie prampia ſuaſufficientia erunt, &amp; capere am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> am perfecti non p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>terint. Every <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> ſhall be ſufficient for them, and being <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> perfect, they ſhall not be able to receiue any more,</hi> ſaith St. <hi>Proſper.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>As many veſſels of diverſe quantities dipt into the Ocean will all be filled, but every one accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to their proper quantitie. Or as divers gueſts at a feaſt are fully ſatiated and filled, yet all doe not eat alike, and receiue the ſame quantitie, but every one according to the ſtrength and meaſure of their ſtomacke: So ſhall it be with the <hi>Elect</hi> in the kingdome of God, in <hi>the day of the Sonne of man,</hi> that day of glorie: all ſhall haue ſatietie of heavenly delights and pleaſures, but every one
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:13754:52" rendition="simple:additions"/>according to their capacitie and meaſure. During their pilgrimage on earth, they walked on pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently in the way of good workes; they hungred and thirſted after righteouſneſſe; but then ſhall they be ſatisfied with life, righteouſneſſe and glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry. How <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> redeemed them with his ſacred bloud, will now ſatiate them with the bread of life, and inebriate them with the wine of his loue. And as the ſweet ſinger of <hi>Iſrael</hi> ſpeaketh,<note place="margin">Pſal. 36.8, 9.</note> 
                  <hi>He will abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dantly ſatisfie them with the fatneſſe of his houſe: and will make them drinke of the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>er of his plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures: for with him is the fountaine of life, and in his light ſhall they ſee light.</hi> They ſhall ſee the light which ſhall never decay, enjoy the life which ſhall never haue an end. For they ſhall ever be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold <hi>Him, who is the light and the life, who is all perfection, all glory, all felicitie, all eternitie, who is all in all.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>To that all ſufficient being, who is his owne eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall being, and the being of all other <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap>, who is Alpha and O<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ega, the beginning and the en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, the firſt and the laſt; To the Creator of the world, the glory of the Angels, the light and life of men; To that infinite fountaine of loue, which hath loved us with an ever laſting loue in Chriſt the ſonne of his loue; To the Father of mercies, the God of all grace, peace and conſolation, be aſcribed of us all goodneſſe, wiſedome, power, prayſe, honour, glorie, adoration, thankeſgiving, for all his bleſſings in Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt, now and in all ages for ever,</hi> Amen.</p>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="license">
            <pb n="96" facs="tcp:13754:53" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>Perlegi Librum h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nc, dignum<expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:abque"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>que</ex>
               </expan> judico qui typis mandetur.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Tho. Weekes</hi> R. P. Epo.</signed>
               <dateline>Lond. Capel. domeſt.</dateline>
            </closer>
            <pb facs="tcp:13754:53"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
